<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A looking glasse for the court. Composed in the Castilian tongue by the Lorde Anthony of Gueuarra Bishop of Mondouent, and chronicler to the Emperour Charles. And out of Castilian drawne into Frenche by Anthony Alaygre. And out of the French tongue into Englishe by Sir Fraunces Briant Knight one of the priuy Chamber, in the raygne of K. Henry the eyght</title>
            <title>Menosprecio de corte. English</title>
            <author>Guevara, Antonio de, Bp., d. 1545?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1575</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02315</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12448</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103507</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839259</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839259</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3663</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02315)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3663)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 318:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A looking glasse for the court. Composed in the Castilian tongue by the Lorde Anthony of Gueuarra Bishop of Mondouent, and chronicler to the Emperour Charles. And out of Castilian drawne into Frenche by Anthony Alaygre. And out of the French tongue into Englishe by Sir Fraunces Briant Knight one of the priuy Chamber, in the raygne of K. Henry the eyght</title>
                  <title>Menosprecio de corte. English</title>
                  <author>Guevara, Antonio de, Bp., d. 1545?</author>
                  <author>Tymme, Thomas, d. 1620.</author>
                  <author>Bryan, Francis, Sir, d. 1550.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>And now newly printed, corrected and set forth wyth sundry apt notes in the margent by T. Tymme minister.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[4], 76 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By Thomas East] for William Norton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1575.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Menosprecio de corte.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC; colophon reads: Printed by VVilliam Norton.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A dispraise of the courtiers life.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Courts and courtiers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Country life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3663:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3663:1"/>
            <p>A looking Glaſſe for the Court.</p>
            <p>Compoſed in the Caſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian tongue by the Lorde Anthony of Gueuarra Biſhop of Mondouent, and Cronicler to the Emperour Charles. And out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſtilian drawne into Frenche by Anthony Alaygre. And out of the French tongue into Engliſhe by Sir Fraunces Briant Knight one of the priuy Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, in the raygne of K. Henry the eyght. And now newly printed, corrected and ſet forth wyth ſundry apt notes in the margent by T. Tymme Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter.</p>
            <p>¶Imprinted at London, for Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Norton. An. 1575.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:3663:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>nor</p>
                  <p>w</p>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of William Norton</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3663:2"/>
            <head>¶To the Right honorable, Iohn, Lord Ruſſell, ſonne and heire ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant to the right Noble Fraunces, Earle of Bedforde, one of the Queenes Maieſties priuie Counſaile, and Knight of the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable order of the Garter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He recommending of this lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and pleaſaunt Treatiſe, the more generally to haue it peruſed (right Honorable) is the cauſe why I haue dedicated the ſame to your Honour. For it being warranted vnder your protection, (in whome ſuch vertues haue their ſeate, that in you is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed the right paterne of true Nobilitie) can not but carry great credit, though the matter of it ſelfe, ſhoulde leſſe deſerue the ſame. It nothing doth diſmaye me for that I being vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to your Honour, haue thus farre preſumed, neyther may this ſeeme any raſhe attempt for that cauſe. For ſuch is the alluring force of vertue, that ſhee conſtrayneth vs to beare ſingular loue and affection, not only to our owne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen by vew of face vnknowne, but alſo to Aliants, which by Lande and Sea are farre ſeuered from vs. Wherefore I being caught with the commendation of your Noble heart, furniſhed with vertue generally noyſed, coulde not but take courage to preſent this Pamphlet vnto your Honours hands, as a most meete Patron for the ſame. In the which you ſhall finde pleaſaunt matter concerning the diſprayſe of the Court, and the commendation of the Rusticall lyfe being eloquently pende by that Reuerende Father in God the Lorde <hi>Anthony</hi> of <hi>Gueuarra,</hi> a man of great learning and grauitie, whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:3663:3"/> name may ſufficiently warrant the worke to be handled with great diſcretion: last and leaſt, my willing traueyle to reuiue the ſame lying as dead, and by tyme worn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lmost cleane a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye. Therefore accept my good will (Ryght Honourable) and if opportunitie ſhall ſerue, hereafter there ſhall greater thinges appeare vnder your Honours name. For this tyme, not to trouble your Honour with longer ſpeache, I take my leaue, recommending my poore payns as the needie Wydowes Myte to your Honourable courteſie,<note place="margin">Mar. 12.42.</note> and courtuouſe acceptaunce: beſeeching Almightie God to giue you increaſe of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and to bleſſe you and your most Noble and vertuous Lady, that ſhe may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioye to hyr comfort and yours, that long deſired and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed fruite and with Anna the Mother of <hi>Samuel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.1.</note> ioyfully prayſe God for the ſame.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours moſt humble</hi> Thomas Tymme.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3663:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <l>IF high eſtate and Noble byrth</l>
            <l>Adournde with learnings lore,</l>
            <l>Deſerue high commendacion</l>
            <l>And merit prayſe therefore:</l>
            <l>If pearles of greateſt pryce deſerue,</l>
            <l>Of ryght in fyneſt golde</l>
            <l>To be coutched and enamelde</l>
            <l>For all men to beholde:</l>
            <l>If wyſedome, or authoritie,</l>
            <l>If knowledge, credit, fame,</l>
            <l>If haultie courage, courtlie grace,</l>
            <l>And myldeneſſe with the ſame,</l>
            <l>May gyue to booke a countenaunce,</l>
            <l>Or make it more regarded:</l>
            <l>I ſay vnto this booke there ought,</l>
            <l>Lyke prayſe to be awarded.</l>
            <l>Whoſe Authour, <hi>Dan Gueuarra,</hi> hight</l>
            <l>A Phoenix of our age:</l>
            <l>To <hi>Charles</hi> the fyfth, late Emperour,</l>
            <l>A Counſayler full ſage.</l>
            <l>And Preacher eke the ſame, and eke</l>
            <l>A Cronicler of Actes:</l>
            <l>Who coulde by ſounde of clanging trumpe</l>
            <l>Emblazon out his factes.</l>
            <l>Who many workes to vs hath left</l>
            <l>For which we better fare.</l>
            <l>Dyrecting vs to vertue, and</l>
            <l>Of vices to beware.</l>
            <l>Acquaynted well with courtly guyſe</l>
            <l>In <hi>Kaiſers</hi> fauour hygh,</l>
            <l>Yet verdict gyues that Countrey lyfe</l>
            <l>Surmounth it farre and nygh.</l>
            <l>Whoſe pithie reaſons, fyled ſpeache,</l>
            <l>And ſugred woordes dyd moue</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:3663:4"/>
            <l>A worthy Knyght of Engliſh Court,</l>
            <l>Whome <hi>Henry</hi> Kyng dyd loue,</l>
            <l>Fyrſt to tranſlate from forrayne phraſe</l>
            <l>Into our mother tonge,</l>
            <l>Inueſting it with Engliſh roabe,</l>
            <l>As good for olde and yonge.</l>
            <l>For pleaſure and for profite both</l>
            <l>To recreate the mynde:</l>
            <l>And reaping thence commoditie,</l>
            <l>Eaſe for themſelues to fynde.</l>
            <l>One not vnlyke to <hi>Xenophon</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Whoſe ſhape his Countrey men</l>
            <l>Set vp with ſworde in ryght hande claſpt,</l>
            <l>In left, a wryting pen.</l>
            <l>In lyke ſorte lyude, this worthy knyght</l>
            <l>In marſhall feates well tryde</l>
            <l>With Launce, Speare, Targe: in tyme of peace</l>
            <l>His penne good workes deſcryde.</l>
            <l>Whoſe worthy paynes, and learned pennes</l>
            <l>I doe commende to thee:</l>
            <l>Whoſe vertues bryghtly ſhyne, and neede</l>
            <l>Not to be prayſde by mee:</l>
            <l>That Myte of labour, which my ſelfe</l>
            <l>Therein beſtowed haue,</l>
            <l>In gentle ſorte accept, for more</l>
            <l>I neyther ſeeke ne craue.</l>
            <l>And ioyne with me in prayer fyrme</l>
            <l>For health, long lyfe, and raygne,</l>
            <l>Of our moſt noble Queene, that ſhee</l>
            <l>On earth, may long remayne.</l>
            <l>To guyde the ſterne of Chriſtian barge</l>
            <l>With Oares of ſacred lore:</l>
            <l>And afterwarde to raygne with Chriſt</l>
            <l>In blyſſe for euermore.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:3663:4"/>
            <head>¶A Table contayning briefly the ſumme of euery Chapter.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>CHAPTER.</hi> 1.</label> OF certaine Courtyers which ought to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playne of none but of themſelues.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>CHAPTER.</hi> 2.</label> That none ought to counſayle another to go to the Court, nor when he is there to come from it, but euery man to chooſe the life that liketh him beſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>CHAPTER.</hi> 3.</label> That a Courtyer ought to leaue the Court for not being in fauour: but being out of it already, that he ought not to ſeeke entertainement there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, that he maye be more vertuous.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>CHAPTER.</hi> 4.</label> Of the lyfe that the Courtyer ought to leade, after that he hath left the Court.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>CHAPTER.</hi> 5.</label> That the Ruſticall lyfe is more quiet and reſtfull, and more beneficiall than that of the Courte.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>CHAPTER.</hi> 6.</label> That in the Village the dayes ſéeme more longe, and the ayer more cleare, and the houſes more reſtfull than in the Courte.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>CHAPTER.</hi> 7.</label> That commonly the Inhabitants of the Villages, be more happy than Courtyers.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>CHAPTER.</hi> 8.</label> That in Prnices Courtes the cuſtome and vſe is to ſpeake of God, and lyue after the worlde.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>CHAPTER.</hi> 9.</label> In the Court fewe amende, but many wax woorſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>CHAPTER.</hi> 10.</label> That a man cannot lyue in the Court without he trouble himſelfe or ſome other.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3663:5"/>
                     <hi>CHAPTER.</hi> 11.</label> That in the Courte thoſe that be graue are praiſed and well eſtéemed, and the other that doe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary not regarded.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>CHAPTER.</hi> 12.</label> That in the Court of Princes all ſay we wyll doe it, but they doe it not.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>CHAPTER.</hi> 13.</label> That there is a ſmall number of them that be good in the Courte, and a great number of good in the common wealth.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>CHAPTER.</hi> 14.</label> Of many affaires in the Court, and that there be better huſbandmen, than co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly is of courtiers.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>CHAPTER.</hi> 15.</label> That amonge Courtyers is neyther kept amitye nor faithfulneſſe: and how much the Court is full of traueyle, of enuy, and rancor.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>CHAPTER.</hi> 16.</label> By howe muche the common wealthes and the Courtes of the time paſt, were more perfite tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Courtes of the time preſent.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>CHAPTER.</hi> 17.</label> Of dyuers Noble and valiaunt men that left the Court and the great Cities, and drewe them to their proper houſes more by wil tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by neceſſity.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>CHAPTER.</hi> 18.</label> The Authour complayneth with great reaſon of the yeares that he loſt in the Courte.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>CHAPTER.</hi> 19.</label> The Authour maketh account of the vertues that he loſt in the Courte.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>CHAPTER.</hi> 20.</label> The Authour taketh his leaue of the worlde wyth great eloquence.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3663:5"/>
            <head>To the right reuerend <hi>and worthy Prelate my Lorde</hi> VVillyam de Prat, bishop of Clere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount, Antony Alaygre ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth greting.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not many daies paſt ſithens I beyng retyred for a time (my good lord) into the vilage, and there taking the commoditie and pleaſure of the faire ſweet fieldes, a certaine frend of myne ſent vnto me a worke in the Caſtilian tongue of the lord Antony of Gueuera biſhop of Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douent, &amp; Chronicler of the Emperour: in reading whereof I founde great pleaſure and profit. The title of the booke is the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſing of the Court, and the prayſe of the life ruſticall, dedicate vnto the king of Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingall in ſuch ſort, that the better to keepe and to hold the wiſe ſentence and erudicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s therein co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined, I employed certain houres after ſupper to tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlate the ſame into fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch, not thinking amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g mine other ſimple works
<pb facs="tcp:3663:6"/> euer to put it abrod, but after that I had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>municate the ſame with ſome of my frends that haue knowledge of the Spaniſh tongue, I thought it not good to leaue it in a corner to make it meat for Rats &amp; Miſe. Now for truth, the firſt exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pler was ſo euil deuided, and the leaues ſo out of order that I gaue charge to the Scriuener that was my nye neighbour to copy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; as who ſhould ſay to write it faire and in order, the which ſo euil went about it, although by ignoraunce he could not enſue the originall, yet for to gette a litle money he ſolde where his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure was the copies ſo vncumly ſet together that I was ſory and repentant that euer I conſumed the time to tranſlate it, till at the laſt moued by the perſuaſion of Annas Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Vicar general, and by Peter Ciſter your aduocate, by them twaine my great frends, I thought it better to preſent to the eyes of all men this euill tranſlated, then to ſuffer lenger thoſe euill exemplers ſo corrupted to my blame in the handes of thoſe that haue no right iudgement, to know from whom the faulte came: wherefore my good Lorde, vnder your prudent fauor and correction
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3663:6"/> I doe aduenture herein my name &amp; fame acording to my knowledge, truſtyng aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly that your only name ſhall ſuffice to vanquiſhe and ſet aſide this ſlaunder, the which ſlaunder as enemie to learned men, ceaſe not to withdrawe thoſe that haue good will and mynde to ſtudie: I ſaye this that as mee ſeemeth it is well worthy that worke of the wyſe biſhop of Spayne be preſented to his ſemblable or ſuperior in learnyng in Fraunce, or rather aboue him knowledge and vertuous maners. I will adde to this, that the graue ſentences and perſwaſion to vertuous lyfe contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in thys booke, deſerue to bee offered to you that are accuſtomed to vſe them after ſuche ſorte that euery man haue playne opinion of you that yee are ſent of God to bee protector and patron of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, troubled and diſpiſed. Therefore (my ſinguler good Lorde, as one of the chiefeſt of the beſt ſorte) I dedicate to you this my little labour, not that I thinke it worthy to come into your handes, but for to be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall witnes that I do owe vnto you my
<pb facs="tcp:3663:7"/> ſeruice with al reuerence, to the which moſt humbly I recommend me. From your Citie of Cleremont this fyrſt day of May. Anno. M.D.xlii.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:3663:7"/>
            <head>A diſpraiſe of the life of <hi>the Courtier, and a commendaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the life of the huſbandman, compoſed in the Caſtilian toungue, by the reuerend father in God, the Lord Antony of Gueuera, bishop of Mondouent, and Chronicler to the Emperour Charles. And out of Caſtilian drawen into Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch by Anthony Alaygre, &amp; now out of the Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch tongue into our maternall language, by ſir Fraunces Bryant knight, one o king Henry the .viii. moſt hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable chamber.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>The firſt Chapiter. Of certaine Courtiers which ought to complaine of none, but of them ſelues.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that the noble prince <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedony</hi> had ouerru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne the <hi>Atheniens,</hi> one a time he being at ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per amonges certaine of his Philoſophers, aſked them which was the greateſt thing in the worlde?
<pb facs="tcp:3663:8"/> One of them anſwered, that to hys thinking it was the water, becauſe there was more of that onely then of any other thinge vnder the ſkye.<note place="margin">The greateſt thing in the worlde defined by Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers.</note> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother ſaid it was the Sunne, ſéeyng his only brightnes doeth ſuffiſe to geue light to the yearth, to the ſtarres, and to the water. Another ſaid it was the great hill <hi>Olympe,</hi> whoſe heigth paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the cloudes. Another ſayd it was the moſt renoumed gyant <hi>Athlas,</hi> on whoſe ſepulcre was builded the fear full mountain <hi>Ethna.</hi> Another ſaid it was <hi>Homer,</hi> that in his life was ſo muche praiſed and after his death ſo muche bewailed, that vii. great cities made warre amonges themſelues for the recouery of his bones, to kepe them as a relike. The laſt and moſt wiſe Philoſopher ſaid, that nothing in this world ought to be called great,<note place="margin">Mans harte is the greateſt thinge in the worlde.</note> but that hart which eſtemeth no great thinges. O high and noble ſentence, ſince there by that it is geuen vs to vnderſtande, that as touching the riches &amp; honor of this world, more is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of him that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3663:8"/> ſettes lyghte by them, then hée that hath the caſt for to get them. <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Liuius</hi> prayſeth and neuer ceaſeth to praiſe, the good Conſull <hi>Marcus Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> in the houſe of whome, came Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours of the <hi>Sannites</hi> for to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer certaine landes that he had of theirs, offering to him for the ſame plentie of Golde and ſiluer: Hée ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in hys hande certaine hearbes to put in his potte for his dinner, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them after this ſorte, ye ſhould haue offered this money to the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes that diſdayne to dreſſe their owne dinners, and not to me that deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth no greater riches then to bee Lord ouer their Lordes.</p>
               <p>Deſerued not this <hi>Marcus Curius</hi> more prayſe in ſetting light thoſe ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentes of Golde of the <hi>Sannites,</hi> than the Conſell <hi>Lucullus</hi> for robbing them of <hi>Spartes?</hi> Deſerued not the wiſe <hi>Crates</hi> more glory for the riches that he caſt in to the Sea than the king <hi>Nabugodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezer</hi> for the treaſure that hée robbed from the temple? To your Iudgement,
<pb facs="tcp:3663:9"/> did not they of the Iles of <hi>Bariares</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue more honor, agreing not to haue among them neither gould nor ſiluer, than the couetouſe <hi>Greekes</hi> that toke by force and pilled the mines of <hi>Spaine?</hi> was not the hart of the good Emperour <hi>Auguſtus</hi> more greate, in ſetting light the Empire, than of his vncle <hi>Iulius Ceaſar,</hi> that did take poſſeſſion?</p>
               <p>It is nedefull to haue wiſdome, experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to order it, cunning to ſet it foorth, and fortune to bring it to good ende: but to vphould and kepe it, it had nede of great ſtrengthe, and for to diſprayſe it, a good harte, bycauſe that which is ſéene with the eyes is more eaſie to diſpraiſe than that thynge which we haue already in our handes. It hath bene ſéene, that many noble me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune ſo much at their deſires, that they haue enterpriſed a thing almoſt impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to attaine, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which after for lacke of good diſcrecio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, were not able to kepe it. Wherby it is to be vnderſtand that the greatnes of the heart doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt ſo much in obtainyng the thing that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3663:9"/> we deſire to haue, as it is to ſet light,<note place="margin">True forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude conſiſteth in mortefying our affctions.</note> &amp; contemne that that one loues beſt. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polonius Thyaneus,</hi> dyd he not diſpiſe his owne proper countrey &amp; trauailed thorowout all <hi>Aſia</hi> for to go to ſée the Philoſopher <hi>Hyarchis</hi> in Ynde?<note place="margin">Abraham in like manner forſoke his own countrey and kinred. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 12.1. Moſes regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not in like manner the ſtatelines of Pharaos courte. <hi>Exod.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Exod.</hi> 10.28. Ambition is to be auoyded as theſe exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples teache.</note> 
                  <hi>Ariſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>totle</hi> leauyng the familiaritie he had w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Alexander,</hi> returned to his owne houſe for to reade Philoſophy. <hi>Nicodius</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing extemed the treaſure that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great king <hi>Cyrus</hi> gaue him for to folowe him in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> warres. The Philoſopher <hi>Anatil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> refuſed thrée times y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> principality of <hi>Athenes,</hi> ſaying: he had rather bée ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good, then a chaſtiſer of the euil. <hi>Cecilius Metellus</hi> a valiaunt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitaine <hi>Roman,</hi> neither would accepte the eſtate of Dictator that to him was geuen, nor the office of Conſull that to him was offered: ſaying,<note place="margin">Prouerbes <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.19.</note> that he would eate in reſt that which with great tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uail he had gotten in the war. Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Dyocleſian</hi> (as it is manifeſt) forſoke with his frée will the Empyre, for no other cauſe but to flée the brute of the common ſpéech, and to liue in
<pb facs="tcp:3663:10"/> reſt at home. Worthy is hée to be prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that hath the harte to care little for an Empire or a realme:<note place="margin">Prouerbes <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.32.</note> but yet more is hée worthy that can ſette light by him ſelfe and not to be gouerned by his owne will: for there is no man in this worlde, but that hée is more in loue with that hée deſireth, then with that he hath:<note place="margin">Couetous me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neuer ſatiſfied</note> but howe couetous or ambici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſo euer any man be, if he trauail x. daies for that which he hath, hee will beſtowe an hundreth to obtain that whiche hée deſireth,<note place="margin">Moſt men miſlyke of their eſtate.</note> becauſe that wée do not beſtow our labor as we ſhuld, but we beſtowe it after our deſires. If we do trauaill, if we be troubled, if we cannot ſlepe, it is not for neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but for to ſatiſfie our wil and appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite. And that is worſt of all, we not contenting our ſelues with that we can do procure to can that that we deſire. O how many haue we ſéen in the court of princes,<note place="margin">Will, hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer throwen mightie men, and brought them from princes courtes to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</note> to whom it had béen better for them that they had béen no lordes of their will, and leſſe of their deſires becauſe ſythens they dyd that they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3663:10"/> might and deſired, begon to doe, that they ought not to doe? If the man that offendes vs ought to aſke pardon, let euery man aſke pardon to himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any other,<note place="margin">Men are to them ſelues the greateſt enemies.</note> for in my life I found neuer none that hurte mée ſo much as my ſelf, I haue béen only the procurer of myne owne hurt.<note place="margin">Preſumption and pryde go together. <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.30. Enuie is the frute of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brideled affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions. <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.5. <hi>and</hi> .11.</note> Who made mée fall into pryde, but mine only preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and fondnes? Who durſt haue pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned my ſorowfull heart with enuye, but lacke of natural gouernement? who durſt haue inflamed myne inwardes with the fyer of yre, if it had not béen my great impacience? what is the cauſe I am ſo great a gurmander, but that my bringyng vp was to delicate? what is the cauſe I haue not departed with my goodes to the poore and néedy, but the exceſſyue loue I had to my ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches? who gaue leaue to my fleſhe to ryſe againſt my foliſh deſire, if my hart had not béen fixed in voluptuous plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures? O my ſoule, of all this domage and open faultes, to whome doe you laye the blame, but to myne owne
<pb facs="tcp:3663:11"/> ſenſualitie? Great folly it is, the thefe being within the houſe, to ſeke for him without: euen ſo it is with vs a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt faulte of experience, when ſeing in vs the blame, and yet charge another with the occaſion:<note place="margin">Reformation of our faultes bringeth qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etnes.</note> by this we ought to perceyue that wée ſhall neuer ceaſe to complaine vntill the tyme we begin to amende. Oh, howe often and many tymes hath vertue fought with the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of our conſciences,<note place="margin">This battaile is in the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, in the which they ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come: but the wicked are ſubdued to ſinne. <hi>Rom. chap.</hi> 7.18. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1.</note> which ſtyrred vs to be good, and our ſenſualitie reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, which is vaine frowardnes, by the which battail folowed a darke corrupt iudgement: but to conclude, we of oure ſelues as of our ſelues are very miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. The Poete <hi>Ouid</hi> reherſeth the louing <hi>Philis</hi> the <hi>Rodian</hi> complaining of her ſelfe &amp; ſayeth: Oh <hi>Demophon,</hi> if I had not beſtowed time to loue thée, and ſiluer and ſhippes for thexpedicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the voiage, thou durſt not wel to haue gone, nor I to haue bewailed thy depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, in ſuche wiſe that with my owne wepons was my body wounded. If we beleue <hi>Ioſephus</hi> in that he did wryte of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3663:11"/> 
                  <hi>Maryana,</hi> &amp; <hi>Homer,</hi> in that he ſayd of <hi>Helene, Plutarch</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſpake of <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opatra. Virgil</hi> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quene <hi>Dydo, Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſt</hi> of <hi>Pollyſene, Zantippe</hi> of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milla, Aſſenarius</hi> of <hi>Clodia:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Men are by nothing more deceyued than by themſelues</note> Al theſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and excellent princes neuer found themſelues ſo deceiued by their louers as they were by beleuing their owne proper counſels, and lightly conſenting to the ſame.</p>
               <p>If to <hi>Suetone, Zantippe</hi> and <hi>Plutarch</hi> we will geue credite and beleue thoſe thynges that they declare of <hi>Pompe, Pyrrhus, Hannyball,</hi> and the Conſull <hi>Marius,</hi> of the Dictator <hi>Caeſar,</hi> of <hi>Mark Antony</hi> &amp; many others we ſhal finde they blamed not fortune ſo much to be vanquiſhed by others, as in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie they were ruled by their owne aduiſe and counſelles. It is true, that often times the opinion of our kinne &amp; frendes maketh vs to enter into buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes out of the waye of reaſon,<note place="margin">Frends often tymes ſeduce from reaſon.</note> not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring but for a foliſhe auauncement of goodes and riches. And at the end when by their ſetting forth one hath enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:3663:12"/> a certaine buſynes of importaunce whiche doeth require ayd and helpe, thoſe ſame bée the laſte that ſhewe them ſelues helping frendes:<note place="margin">Many are frendes in wordes, but fewe are to be founde in dede</note> whiche is the occaſion many tymes that men cannot returne from enterpriſyng ſuch thinges as neither ſhall growe to their honor nor profite. Many men ſay that they haue enemies, recountyng them often without findyng number: Although it be true if it be well noted, that none haue oftener or a greater ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my than him ſelf. And the moſt grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt daunger that I ſée,<note place="margin">Clyming cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth fallinge.</note> is that vnder the ſhadowe to preferre and make better my ſelfe, my ſelfe is the cauſe of my deſtruction. The Philoſpher <hi>Neotidas</hi> on a tyme being aſked which was the beſt counſell that a man might take, anſwered, The counſell of others with the diſpraiſyng of his owne:<note place="margin">We muſt not ſtande in our owne conceit.</note> and he ſheweth the cauſe, for that the corrupcion of man is ſuche, that often hee ſearcheth in him ſelfe with greate paine that whiche in the head of another, hée fyndeth wyth
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3663:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> great eaſe. Then it foloweth, that in the beſt tyme of our lyfe our owne lyfe deceiueth vs, the euil commeth fourth on euery ſyde, heauy thoughtes ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take vs, our frendes leaue vs,<note place="margin">A liuely deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cription of the miſeries of mans life.</note> perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors torment vs, troubles make an end of vs, ambicion burieth vs. If wée beholde thys thyng: what wee bée: whereof we bée: and wherefore wée bée, we ſhall fynde that our beginnyng is obliuion, our middle age trauayle, the ende ſorow, and altogether an open errour. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſée how heauy is the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers lyfe,<note place="margin">The courty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers life is full of perills.</note> as alſo howe daungerous the way is, where as be ſtones to ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at, myer to ſticke faſt in, yſe for to fall on, pathwayes for to loſe hym in, water for to paſſe thorow, théeues for to be afrayd of, great affaires and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines to doe, ſo that hard it is for any to goe there as they would, and more harde to aryue there as they deſire. All theſe thinges haue we ſayd, to the intent that the Courtiers may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that neither I nor they can choſe the good way &amp; leaue the euil, voyd that
<pb facs="tcp:3663:13"/> that hurtes vs, and conſerue that which profiteth vs, folow reaſon and plucke away the occaſion: but if by chaunſe ſome good fal to vs,<note place="margin">Blynde for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune prayſed for proſperity, and blamed for aduerſitie.</note> we thanke fortune, and if euill come to vs, then we do put the fault in her.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſecond Chapiter ¶ How that none ought to counſell a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> other to go to the Court, nor when he is there to come from it, but euery man to choſe the life that beſt he liketh.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Riſtarch</hi> the great Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher of <hi>Theban,</hi> ſayd, That, tyme and man was ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, that hard it was for the moſt wiſe to chuſe that to them which was good, and to kepe them from that which to them is euil.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">One thing is not pleaſant to all men.</note>There is nothing more true, for we ſée dayly, with the ſame that one is hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, another falleth ſicke: with that that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3663:13"/> one waxeth better, another waxeth worſe: with that that one is amended, another is put downe: and to conclude, with that litle thing that one is content withall another is in diſpaire. The ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Alchymus</hi> was by his <hi>Moecoenas</hi> king <hi>Demetrius,</hi> aſked wherein ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt the greateſt trauail of the worlde? He anſwered, ther is few thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges but in them there is either trauail or ſuſpicion,<note place="margin">A minde neuer ſatiſfied hath exceſſiue tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uail.</note> but aboue all the mooſte exceſſiue trauail that a man may haue, is neuer to be ſatiſfied. And that this is true, we perceiue that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a litle thing contenteth vs, how litle ſoeuer it be, we make it our paradice with the reſt of our life: which ſeldome chaunſeth to fewe men, becauſe that liuyng as we liue, not being contented, we would aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaie and knowe if it were good to be a king, a prince, a knight, a maried man,<note place="margin">No man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with his eſtate.</note> a religious or a marchaunt, a laborer, a ſhepeherd, or of ſome other eſtate. And at the ende, when al is proued, it ſhal be harde to finde where we would reſt, ſo vnconſtaunt is the lightnes of men.
<pb facs="tcp:3663:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> The wiſe determineth that to choſe the beſt is the meane. A ſimple creature is lightly contented with a ſmall thing,<note place="margin">The poore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tente them ſelues with that which the riche &amp; migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie contemne.</note> but he that hath a great harte, thynkes that pouertie is a greuous life, like as they that be of high eſtate feare the fall of fortune. <hi>Plato</hi> was in hys young yeres very worldely, as he that had ſéene much, aſwell in the warres as in offices, in whiche he was vſed, and alſo in handy craftes. On a time it was aſked him wherin he had found moſt quietnes and reſt? He anſwered, there is no eſtate of life wherein is not mutabilitie, there is no honor where is no peril,<note place="margin">There is no roaſe without a thorne, nor any pleaſure but it is mixte with payne.</note> no riches where is no trauail, no proſperitie but it endeth, nor alſo pleſure but faileth: but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all is ſaid, I neuer fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo much quietnes of minde, as ſince I left myne offices in Cities, withdrawing me to my bookes: ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as long as we liue ſeruauntes of the world, we deſire al, we proue all, we procure all, then all thinges are well ſéene and taſted, &amp; all thinges do anoye vs: the greateſt part of our diſquietnes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3663:14"/> commeth hereof, that the aboundaunce we haue, ſéemeth to vs litle, and the litle of others, ſéemeth to vs much.<note place="margin">We miſlyke all that we haue our ſelues, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend that which other enioye.</note> We ſaye that our wealth is trauayle, and that the euill happe of others is reſt: we condemne others actes and wée allow our owne: we watche to gette ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what, and ſodeinly we ſléepe to léeſe it agayne: we imagine that all men liues content, and we alone néedy: And yet the worſt is, we beleue that we dream, and put not our truſt in that we ſée be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyen. What way one ought to follow or what eſtate hee oughte to choſe, none can well knowe nor coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile, becauſe the thyng is ſo trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and without good iudgement, by which many are deceiued.<note place="margin">Mans life on earth, full of troubles.</note> If the ſailing on the ſea be daungerous, ſo is the wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king on the earth troubleous.</p>
               <p>As touching our lyfe, we ſée that he that is whole, dayly falleth ſicke, the ſicke dyeth, ſome other ſcapeth deadly daungers, &amp; ſome others lyngers forth to death.<note place="margin">Better is he that hal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>th in the way, then he that runneth out of the way</note> As touchyng the waifa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng men, aſſone commeth he to his
<pb facs="tcp:3663:15"/> lodging that goeth ſoftly, as he that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth haſtely and loſeth his way. He that is in fauor, liuing in ſlothfull reſt, had as much neede of vpholding, as he that continually ſweates in trauail. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I conclude,<note place="margin">The certainty of all thinges is, that all thinges are vncertaine.</note> that there is nothing in this worlde ſo certain, as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all thinges are vncertaine.</p>
               <p>Then let vs returne to that we ſpake of: It is ſaid that it is fearefull, to cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell any to marry, to ſtudy, to go to the war, or to take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him any other thing, then that he is called to: becauſe in this caſe none is ſo apte to receiue,<note place="margin">man likes beſt of that to the which he is in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clined.</note> that which to him is ſaid as he is to receiue that which he is naturally inclyned to. <hi>Plutarch</hi> greatly praiſeth in his booke of common welth, the good Philoſopher <hi>Plato</hi> (and not without cauſe) for hee vſed a greate policy, which was, that there was no you<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g man entred into his ſchoole,<note place="margin">Plato proued the inclinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ſcollers before he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertayned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> but firſt hée would proue him whether he was enclined to lernyng or no, ſo that thoſe that he thought not apte to ſtudy, he ſent them backe, cauſyng them to vſe their liues in the common
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3663:15"/> welth. <hi>Alcibiades</hi> the <hi>Greeke</hi> may be a ſufficient witneſſe vnto you, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though hée was young brought to the ſchoole, and taught of a diſcrete maiſter, yet notwithſtanding his inclinacion was ſuch, that he profeſſed himſelf who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the warres.<note place="margin">The courtier is vnfit to be a ſhepherde, &amp; the ſheperd as vnmeete for a courtier.</note> To him that is borne to weare a ſwerde by his ſide, it ſemeth him ill to wear a tippet about his necke and hée that loueth to kepe ſheepe, the court is nothing fitte for him. To her that deſireth mariage, it is hard to kepe her chaſt: He that loueth to be a barber, why ſhould he be made a Paynter. To counſell our frend to leaue a crafte for to liue by, is but well done: but eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to appoint him what crafte he ought to lerne, that me thynketh worthy to be reproued. The <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to all fathers vpon great paines, to putte none of their children to any craft till they were .xiiij. yeres of age to ſée that in the age of diſcretion what their nature was enclined to. Let vs leaue this long communication, and ſpeake of that we ought to aduertiſe the redar
<pb facs="tcp:3663:16"/> of: to counſell any to leaue the court, ſuche counſel I thinke not beſt to geue, nor yet wiſedome for other to take, ſeyng that there is doubte to counſell any in that they ought to do: Howbeit myne aduice is,<note place="margin">Sage perſons ſhould liue in a quiet ſtate.</note> that the ſage perſons choſe to liue in a quiet ſtate, and to dwell in ſuche a place, that they may leade a life without reproche, and chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianly to dye. Oftentimes men do remoue from one countrey to another, from one toune to another, from one ſtrete, from one houſe, from one companye to another: but to conclud, if that he had peine in the one, hée doeth complaine himſelf vtterly of the wronges of the others: And this is the reaſon, becauſe he layeth the faulte to the nature of the countrey, whiche nothing els is but his owne euil na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. What more ſhal we ſay, but in Courtes,<note place="margin">In Courtes &amp; in moſt places vertu is blamed and vice vncorrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> in cyties, in villages, and in other places, is ſéene the vertuous and the diſcrete corrected, and the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious not blamed. The wicked with their wickednes ſerche by all
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3663:16"/> meanes to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues worſe. And likewiſe doo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertuous with their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, make themſelues better in what ſtate ſoeuer they be called. As for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, there is no charge in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church ſo daungerous but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a good conſcience can auoyd it, but a weake or corrupt conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence may ſoone be caſt away:<note place="margin">Good and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil may be ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken from one and the ſelfe ſame thing.</note> Like as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wilde roſe from whence y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Bee fetcheth her hony, &amp; likewiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Spider her poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. The prince may do his deuor doing iuſtice &amp; not vſing tyranny: The ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of armes going to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> war &amp; not hurting the poore people: The religious may be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templatiue in their cloiſter w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging. The maried ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may liue well in his houſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out aduoutry. The rich ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geueth his goodes for Gods ſake with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out vſury: The laborer in working, the ſhepeherd in keping his ſheepe without hurting his neighbours, &amp; in like caſe of others. And to proue that it is true by the Scripture in the ſtate of Kynges, <hi>Dauid</hi> was good, and <hi>Saull</hi> euyll, to the eſtate of Prieſtes, <hi>Mathias</hi> good, and <hi>Obnias</hi> naught. Of Prophetes,
<pb facs="tcp:3663:17"/> 
                  <hi>Daniel</hi> good,<note place="margin">Of all eſtates ſome good &amp; ſome euell.</note> 
                  <hi>Balam</hi> euill, Of Shepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herdes <hi>Abell</hi> good, <hi>Abimilech</hi> euill, Of wydowes <hi>Iudith</hi> good, <hi>Iezabell</hi> euill, Of rich, <hi>Iob</hi> good, <hi>Naball</hi> naught: Lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe of the Apoſtles, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> good, <hi>Iudas</hi> was reproued. Then perceiue to what eſtate ſoeuer a man commeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, be it good or euill, the eſtate ſheweth not the man,<note place="margin">Inclination <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and not the ſtate.</note> but the inclination of the parſon. If we ſhould counſell any man to liue in the village, he would ſay hée cannot agrée with them of the village, if yée will counſell him to leaue the Court, he will ſay that he hath a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand buſineſſes to doe there: If hée bée counſailed to ſerue any great Lord: he will ſay that he hath nothyng where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to finde him: If we aduiſe him to be a religious, he will ſay that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ryſe early: If to marry, he will ſay it wil gréeue him to heare his litle chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren crye and wéepe: To goe to ſtudye it would trouble his braine: If he were counſayled to withdrawe hym to his houſe, he would ſay hée could not lyue without company. Then preſuppoſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3663:17"/> that which is ſayd, that none ought to counſail any to choſe the lyfe he will take concerning his honor &amp; the wealth of his lyfe, bicauſe afterwarde he will more complayne him, of the counſell that he hath taken, then of the euil that he hath ſuffered.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>The .iij. Chapiter. ¶How that a Courtier ought to leaue the Court for not beyng in fauor, but beyng out of the Court already that he ought not to ſeeke entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there againe that he may be more vertuous.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PVblius Minus</hi> ſayth in his Annota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions that we ought to thinke ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dayes on that which we entend to doe in one day. The kyng <hi>Demetrius,</hi> ſonne of <hi>Antigonus</hi> was aſked by one of his Capitaynes named <hi>Patroclus,</hi> wherefore he gaue not battail to hys enemy <hi>Ptolome,</hi> ſéeyng hys ſtrength, his witte and his number of men? He
<pb facs="tcp:3663:18"/> anſwered,<note place="margin">Aduice &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſail ought to be had before we take any thing in hand</note> that a déed once don, is hard to call backe againe, and before a man begin a harde enterpriſe, he had néed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of long counſaile.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Agiſelaus</hi> a wiſe Capitain of the <hi>Lyca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oniens,</hi> beyng forced to anſwere the Ambaſſadors of the <hi>Thebeans</hi> ſaid: Know not you O <hi>Thebeans</hi> that to determine a thing of importaunce, nothing is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then long ſtudy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> doth greatly prayſe the life of <hi>Sertoreius</hi> in that he was not raſhe in determinyng, but graue in enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing. <hi>Suetone</hi> ſayeth that Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Auguſt</hi> was neuer haſty to get frends, but very diligent to kéepe them when he had them. Of theſe enſam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, note what daunger he falleth in, that is haſty in buſineſſes and quicke in counſels.</p>
               <p>None will wear a garment if it be not ſowed: nor eate the fruit, if it be not rype: nor drinke the wyne, if it be not cleare: nor eat the fleſh if it be not dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: nor warme him with wood, if it be not drye: Wherfore the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do we coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſail
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3663:18"/> vs with grene counſail, which ſooner ſhall ſmudder vs then warme vs. The wiſe man ought to haue before his eyen a ſober deliberacion in his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, for if he thinke one houre of that which he would ſay, he had néede think x. of that that he would doe:<note place="margin">Wordes may be called backe againe: but deedes finiſhed cannot ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be reuoked</note> wordes be but wordes, they may bée corrected, but neuer the vnconſidered déede. The faulte of this, is that euery man ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyeth to ſpeake, to diſpute, to iudge, but none to liue well, nor yet to dye vertuouſlye.<note place="margin">Vertuous life not regarded Stubbornes, wilfulnes, and fickelnes are to be ſhunned in any enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryſe.</note> The graue perſons that will conſerue their auctoritie maye not be teſtie or ſtubburn in ſuch things as they enterpriſe nor wilfull in that they take in hande, nor fickill in that they begin: for one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greateſt faultes that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may haue, is not to bée founde true of his worde, &amp; inconſtant in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath begun.<note place="margin">Conſtancie ought to be in a man of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble harts.</note> A noble hart ought to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which he is charged w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, and if it be iuſt &amp; reaſonable ſoner to die, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not to do it: by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which noble harts are knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> If it were a thing hard &amp; almoſt impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible <hi>Achilles</hi> to flee <hi>Hector: Agiſalus</hi> to
<pb facs="tcp:3663:19"/> ouercome <hi>Brantes:</hi> to <hi>Alexander, Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius:</hi> to <hi>Caeſar Pompeius:</hi> to <hi>Auguſtus, Marcus Antonius:</hi> to <hi>Silla, Mithridates:</hi> to <hi>Scipion Hanniball:</hi> and to the good <hi>Troyan Dacebalus:</hi> theſe noble prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces had neuer béen ſo much eſtéemed as they bée, but that they vttered their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble courage: Then, good aduice ioyned with a noble harte, ought to gouerne great enterpriſes. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to our purpoſe, my maiſter the courtier ſayth,<note place="margin">The courtear miſlyketh his eſtate, often times, and yet continueth therein.</note> he will leaue the curſed lyfe of the court, and go dye at home, ſaying, that to liue in ſuch trouble is a continuall death. O how many and often tymes haue I harde theſe faire wordes, that neuer were fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, excuſing them onely by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiny of the court, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which they were laſt glued. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that a courtier lackes money, that any man doth him diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or that he hath loſt his proces: God knoweth how many othes he maketh that he will forſake all, not to leaue his euil condicions, but becauſe that his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines goeth backewarde: but long his purpoſe laſteth not, for if our courtier
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3663:19"/> hap to come to wealth, or that he be aduaunced by his prince, ye ſhal ſée his former promiſes to waxe colde, his wil and his deſire to remaine there in ſuch wiſe that ye would iudge him to be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally borne there.<note place="margin">Fauour and couetouſnes guide the courtier.</note> Fauor and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes guide the Courtier, ſo that one groweth with the other, and at the ende conuerted from the maner of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to Courtiers.<note place="margin">Welth and beggarie are to be had in the courte.</note> For all men knowe that the court is a place where men may get wealth, &amp; lykewiſe the place of mens vndoyng: We haue already reherſed the occaſions why men doe withdrawe them from the court, ſome for lacke of money, ſome for pouertie, or not being in fauor, or for age, al theſe thinges be of neceſſitie and nothing of free will, nor yet praiſe to them that ſo withdrawe them for the cauſes afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd: but the true leuing of the Court,<note place="margin">Wee ſhoulde forſake that which is euell before euell for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſake vs.</note> and of the worlde is, when the courtier is young, ſtrong, in fauor, riche, and in health, then with good harte to leaue the courte, to fynde in other places honeſt reſt after his degrée is prayſe worthy.
<pb facs="tcp:3663:20"/> This is ſayd, to the entent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hée which leaueth the court, ſhuld leaue it merily and without repenting, for feare that after his ſorowe is paſt, he would be aſhamed to returne to the ſame, where he may chaunſe to haue great buſines.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Deedes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire long re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</note>The proude and vnpacient man doth many thinges in a day whiche he had neede to mourne for all the daies of his life. A colloricke heade is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing meete for the court for if he will be reuenged of the ſhames, iniuries, craftes,<note place="margin">More iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ar offered in one houre in the court, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a man can reuenge in ten yeares.</note> and wronges, that in the court he ſhall fynde, let him truſt that hée ſhall ſuffre more in one houre, then he ſhalbe able to reuenge in ten yere: Whoſoeuer leaueth the court let him leaue it for euermore-becauſe that if he will returne to it again, and leaue his dwelling in the countrey, he may be likened to him, that hath a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall Ague: He that ſinnes and mendes and after returnes againe to ſinne, that ſinne is more greuous then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt. In likewiſe to leaue the courte and after returne to it, is ſo open a faulte that it
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3663:20"/> cannot be hid, excepte ye will ſay, hée goeth to ſell vertue and to by riches.</p>
               <p>To our purpoſe, if we ſhuld aſke of an auncient man, what hath béen the whole courſe of his life, and that hée would anſwere vs, he hath enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed muche, wandred, ſpoken, ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, founde and loſt. &amp;c. We would ſaye that his life hath béen a diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling folly.<note place="margin">The life of a Courtier is diſſembling folly.</note> What ſhall we ſay then of our inconſtant Courtiers that daily do the ſame thinges? whiche forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelues, for the obteinyng of a litle fauour, do againſt nature, flatter, and begge. Remember aboue all things gentle reader here andels where,<note place="margin">That which is ſpoken in this booke, concerning the diſpraiſe of Courtiers, is ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt the vndiſcrete Courtiers. The hart is vnſatiſfied when the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy is wearie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> that I ſpeke not but of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vndiſcrete Courtiers that cannot refraine their appetite with an honeſt contentacion: whiche thing moſt chiefly cauſeth many ſage and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete perſons to geue ouer the Courte, becauſe to refraine the wil of the heart, is a greater paine then to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body is ſoone wery of ſinning, but the heart is neuer ſatyſfied in deſiryng: One may knowe eaſily the compleccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3663:21"/> of the body, but the mynde of the heart neuer, and to contenting leſſe, for the heart at euery inſtaunt requireth now one thing now another, and within a litle time after forgetteth all. O diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling heart that vnder a pretence to be clere and ioyfull, maketh men to iudge that hypocriſy is deuocion, ambicion nobilitie, auarice huſbandry, crueltie zeale of iuſtice, much babling eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, foliſhnes grauitie, and diſſolucion dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence: To conclude, that euery man ought to know how much he may doe: if a man know him ſelfe to be ambici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,<note place="margin">Ambicious impacient and couetous men are meete for the courte. A contented peaceable and quiet man is meete for the towne.</note> impacient, and couetous, let him go hardely to the court: And contrary, if the courtier feele his nature content, pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable, and deſiring reſt and quietnes, let him be dwellyng in the village, and he ſhall well knowe that he neuer knew how to liue, till he had drawen hym ſelf from the Court.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:3663:21"/>
               <head>The .iiii. Chapiter. Of the life that the Courtier ought to leade, after that he hath lefte the Court.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Yronydes</hi> a wiſe &amp; ſage Philoſopher, Capitain of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Boheciens</hi> ſayd, that the prudence of a man was as well knowen by retiring from the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, as in choſing of the good,<note place="margin">Wiſedom con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in choo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſing the good and ſhunning the euil.</note> foraſmuch as vnder the euill commonly the good can not be hid, but vnder the pretence of good much euill may be diſſembled: euen much lyke as the Antheme that beginnes <hi>Per ſignum crucis</hi> and endes in <hi>Sathanas</hi> and <hi>Barrabas:</hi> In like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the great euils haue their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by ſome pretence of fayned good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, in ſuch ſort that they be cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfeict much lyke Maſkers, wrapt in ſwetnes as purging pilles, and gilt as is the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barbe. There is no man I thinke ſo mad that kepeth not himſelf in aſmuch as he can from catching euil, and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb facs="tcp:3663:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> from open euil: but contrariwiſe, it were wiſedome to kéepe him from that which is not altogether good.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, cauſing himſelf to be healed of certaine woundes that he had receiued in battail, was reproued of his great minion <hi>Parmeno</hi> for put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelf into great hazard in the warre:<note place="margin">Frendes fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned are more perillous than open enemies</note> To whom <hi>Alexander</hi> ſayd, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure me my frende <hi>Parmeno</hi> of thoſe that be diſſembling frendes, for I wil be ware of them that be my ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enemies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alcibyades, Agiſelaus, Purrhus, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigonus, Lentulus,</hi> and <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> were ſo circumſpecte in theſe thinges that they were alwayes vanquiſhers, and died in the handes of their frendes, and ſpecially becauſe they choſe the good and lefte the euil.</p>
               <p>Then he that leaueth the court ought not only for to ſée what he leaueth, but alſo what he taketh, conſidering that as much or more hard it is to content him hauing left the court, as it was a fore in the deſiryng to bée in the court: what profiteth it to leaue the Court
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3663:22"/> wery &amp; troubled, If thy hart can finde no reſt in the place whether thou reſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt? Our body fulfilled with meates is led where one will haue it, but the heart is neuer ſatiſfied with deſiryng,<note place="margin">An ambicious hart is neuer ſatiſfied.</note> and wold (if he might) be in fauor with princes of the courte, and on the other ſide at his eaſe in the village. If the Courtier dayly haue mynde beyng at home, of the paſſions &amp; afflictions that he had in the Court, it had béen better for him neuer to haue gone from it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that in remembring them, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king is more pricking, and the mynde weaker to reſiſt them.</p>
               <p>In the court of princes chaunſes of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tymes that lacke of money or other great buſines makes a man abſtayne from doyng euil,<note place="margin">Want of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney maketh ſome forſake the court.</note> the which being after in his houſe doeth ſuch déedes vnſeeme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a gentleman, that they deſerue to be corrected, yea, and bitterly puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</p>
               <p>There bée alſo another ſorte of men that forſakes the Court to bée more idle at home:<note place="margin">Idlenes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth other ſome to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the court</note> And ſuch would be
<pb facs="tcp:3663:23"/> reiected fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the nomber of honeſt men, ſeing they choſe that time for their pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe to ſinne in the village, fearing to be infamed or diſhonored in the court, and yet beyng in the countrey liues with ſhame forgetting all reaſon. To exchue theſe thinges he that leaueth the Court ought to leaue hys percialitie that he hath folowed, and to forget all paſſions: otherwiſe he ſhall lament the ſwéete bitternes that he leaues, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayle the life that he hath begunne. This is true, that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> court are more occaſions geuen to deſtroy a man,<note place="margin">There are more occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the court of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction than there are in a priuate houſe.</note> then are at home in his owne houſe to ſaue him. It is a ſmall profite to the courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the chaunging of his dwelling, vnles by the ſame meanes he change his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicions. When the courtier ſaith I wil withdrawe me to my countrey and go dye at home, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is wel ſaid: but this ſhal ſuffice that he honeſtly withdraw him ſelf, without determining there to dye. This mortall life is to vs ſo apointed,<note place="margin">We muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende our liues, and not curſe them.</note> that we ought not to purſue it with ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, but that we are bounde to amend
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3663:23"/> it. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Iob</hi> ſaid <hi>Tedet animam meam vite mee,</hi> it was not for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys life weri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, but becauſe hée did not ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it.</p>
               <p>Whoſoeuer leaueth the court may be boulde to ſay that he goeth not to die: but may wel thinke he hath eſcaped from a fayre priſon, from a confuſed life, from a daungerous ſickenes, from a ſuſpicious conuerſacion, from a greate ſepulchre,<note place="margin">Many perils ſhooned by for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſakinge the courte. Death is in the court, and life at home.</note> and from a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uail without ende. The wyſeſt being in the court may ſay euery day that they dye, and at their houſes in the countrey that they liue. And the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is: that being in the court, thoſe neceſſary thynges that are to be done in the worlde, cannot be done as they would, nor when they would, for lacke of libertie. Yet I will not ſay,<note place="margin">Ther is more good will in the court to doe good, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> libertie to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the ſame.</note> but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in the courte doo theyr deuor to doe as they would, but I dare affirme that for x. pound weight they haue of honeſt will, they haue not halfe an ounce of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt libertie.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe, let him that forſakes the Court ſet a wiſe order in ſuch buſines
<pb facs="tcp:3663:24"/> that he hath to do, calling to minde that to go home to his countrey néedes no long iorney,<note place="margin">Euil cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes gotten in the court are hardly left.</note> but to diſpoyle him ſelfe of the euil clothes of the Court néedes a wonder long time. For like as vices in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>creaſe in a man litle and litle, ſo is it meete to roote them out by litle &amp; litle. This ought the courtier to do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mindes to rule himſelfe, plucke vp by litle pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the moſt notable faultes that are in him, and ſo preately diſpatch himſelf of one vice to day, &amp; from another to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, in ſuch ſorte that when one vice takes his leaue and is gon, ſtraightway a vertue doe enter in his ſteade, ſo that in proces he may goe from good to bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The courtier is in nothing more de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiued then in liuing a wilde and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton life, parauenture the ſpace of .xx. or xxx. yeares, thinketh in a yeare or two to become ſage and graue,<note place="margin">Vertue is dif<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ferred vntil age, by the Courtier.</note> aſwell as though he applied all his life in a ſober and ſad life, &amp; truely that happeneth for lacke of good iudgement, for it behoueth without compariſon a lenger tyme for to learn to caſt away vice, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to learne
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3663:24"/> vertue:<note place="margin">Vices come merily: but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part hardly.</note> conſidering that vices enter our gates laughing, and goeth out from our houſe weping and lamenting. O how much gréeueth it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ambicious courtier, when he can not commaund as he was wont to doo? the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it may be ſayd, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> court is requiſite to a good heart, and a good witte to obtaine reſt.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that leaue the Court for fainte heart, be of that nature that it is more painefull to them to ſée themſelues ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from the Court, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ioye was when they were in the court: which ſayd perſons if they would folow mine aduice and counſail ſhould not onely leaue the court, but forget it vtterly for euer. And farther, the courtier ought to retyre in ſuche maner that hée may come to the Court againe, if the feare and ſtudy in ordering of his houſeholde conſtrayne him eftſones for to deſire the voluptuouſnes of the court. In the heart of the prudent courtier that forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the court,<note place="margin">Courtiers gape after Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprickes.</note> when there falleth bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprickes or other great offices, the affections and deſires of the mynde
<pb facs="tcp:3663:25"/> ryngeth <hi>alarme,</hi> when he ſhall thinke if I had not come awaye ſo ſoone, that office or that dignitie had been myne: but he again remembring that many ſuche thinges hath fallen which he had not: ſo likewiſe might he haue in the ſtede of ye, a plain nay, of that which fell when he was gone. Then, is it not muche better to ouerſee and trauaile his owne houſe then to haue ſuche a ſhamefull denial in the court?</p>
               <p>Therfore deſtinies of the courtiers are ſo prompte and ready that for the moſt parte one is conſtrained to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe them more by neceſſitie, then by will, and in that meane while their purpoſe is at an ende before they them ſelues beware therof, For when the Courtier commeth to be at quiet with himſelfe, aboue all thinges it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that he take hede of peſteryng of himſelfe,<note place="margin">An admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyered courtier</note> for if he did liue in the court euil willed, let him take hede, that in the village he diſpaire not, by reaſon of charge, the importunitie of his wife, of his children, and the fautes of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3663:25"/> the grudging of his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours may parcaſe make him aſtonied: but to thinke again, that being eſcaped from the daungerous golfe of the court, he may repute him ſelfe halfe a God. And beſides this,<note place="margin">No place, or ſtate, is free from troubles</note> none ought to thinke that he dwelling in a village in the countrey ſhall putte awaye all trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and diſpleaſures, for it can not be, but he that neuer fell in the croked and rough way may happen to ſtumble in the plaine way and breake his necke: and therfore it is neceſſary that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiryng from the court, take the time as it ſhall come, that he may the more oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupie him ſelfe in vertuous exerciſe, to the entent that to muche reſt, and to much buſines of minde let him not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the great good that commeth of this,<note place="margin">Contentacion of mynde brin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth great profite.</note> to be well contented with a litle. Ioyne vnto this alſo that ther is none ſo much enemye vnto vertue as is idlenes, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche idlenes bée taken in the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thoughtes ſuperfluous,<note place="margin">Idlenes is an enemie to ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</note> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the diſtruccion of men.</p>
               <p>To the purpoſe, hath not the cour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tier
<pb facs="tcp:3663:26"/> cauſe to complayne,<note place="margin">The life of the courtier is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picuriſiue.</note> that occupieth himſelf in nothing but in eatyng, drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng, and ſleaping, and in the meane ſeaſon his better age, that is to ſay, his youth conſumeth away, as the fume of ſmoke, which proceeds of idlenes in the court and doyng nothing?<note place="margin">Time is euil ſpent in the court.</note> where con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe hée might in the village ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe himſelf to his honor, &amp; to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> health of his body &amp; profite of his neighbour.</p>
               <p>In like maner alſo, the courtier that withdraweth himſelf ſhould vſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of ſuch as be graue, ſage &amp; honeſt, to the entent that in the ſteade of lyers,<note place="margin">Lyers, flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flers are in the court.</note> flatterers, and triflers, which he was aſſociate withall in the court, he may be accompanyed in the village with wyſe and ſage frendes, or at the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt with good bookes, whereby in the lokyng of them he may vertuouſly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploye the reſidue of his tyme,<note place="margin">In a priuate houſe a man may be occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyed in many godly exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes which in the court he cannot vſe.</note> and with ſobrietie entertaine euery man, that men may ſay he is come from the court to pleaſe the good, and not to rule. And if parcaſe one would make him baylief in the village, or ſome other publique
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3663:26"/> officer, I would counſail him to take heede thereof as he would of the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, for becauſe there is nothing ſo troubleous nor ſo hard a burden to the mynde as to take charge of the rude and ſimple. I doe not ſay nay, but that he may &amp; ought to helpe the poore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the village with ſuche know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege as he hath learned in the court, or had before hee came there, when they ſhall haue neede, eyther for loue or for money. Alſo if they bée at variaunce, helpe to appeace the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: if they be euil in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated, defend them. And this doyng, he ſhalbe eſtéemed of the commons &amp; prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the wiſe and prudent.<note place="margin">Three things are to be ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>red courtier.</note> Aboue all thinges beware of prodigall apparell, ſuperfluous banquetes, and delicate meates, and ſtrong or precious wynes. For the abſenting from the court ought to be to none other purpoſe but to liue ſoberly in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> village,<note place="margin">A priuate houſe ought not to be a court.</note> or els ſhall he make of the village the court, which ſhould make of the court, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> village. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tier retyred from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> court ought to haue in ſinguler co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mercy, as to viſit
<pb facs="tcp:3663:27"/> Hoſpitalles,<note place="margin">Charitable deedes to be practiſed of all men.</note> ſuccor the poore, counſail the Orphans, viſite the priſoners, read the holy ſcripture, and finally that hee ſtudy to diſpoſe his goodes vertuouſlye during his life, for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhalbe dead, euery man will clayme his goodes,<note place="margin">Many loue our goodes but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ewe or none care for our ſoule.</note> but none will nor can diſcharge his ſoule. And moſt chiefly, let the courtier that goeth from the court occupye himſelfe vertuouſly to dye. All theſe thinges that I haue ſayd, let no man ſay that they be more eaſy to reade then to do: for if we will enforce our ſelues, we are more then our ſelues, and doe not then well remember our ſelues.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>The .v. Chapiter. ¶That the ruſticall lyfe is more quiet and reſtfull and more beneficiall then that of the court.</head>
               <p>THe village whereof we ſpeake and the demaines thereof, Put we the caſe that it were all frée and not ſubiect to any Lord (as certain there be ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uileged)
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3663:27"/> that euery man there lyeth in his owne houſe, whether it be by ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, or that he haue bought it fréely without doyng any homage or ſeruice to any man. This I dare ſay, the courtier hath not, nor is not in ſuch frée libertie in reſpecte of ſuch as be of the village, foraſmuch as of very neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, my maiſter the courtier muſt win the Marſhall or Harbengar of the lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, and muſt receiue at his handes the billet to come to his lodging, and that late ynough and wery to his hoſt, breake open dores, beat downe walles,<note place="margin">Shamefull ſhiftes of cour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiers.</note> diſorder houſes, burne impleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, and ſometyme beat the good man, &amp; defyle the wife. O how happy is he that hath wherwithal to liue in the village with out troubling both of himſelf and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſondry places, without ſéeking of ſo many lodginges, without aſſayes of ſo many ſtraunge occaſions of ſtraunge men, without wéeping of any perſon, but is content with a meane eſtate, and is deliuered of all ſuch breakebraines. Another benefite of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey is this,
<pb facs="tcp:3663:28"/> that the gentleman or burges that there doth inhabite may be one of the chief or chiefeſt, either in bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie, honor, or auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie,<note place="margin">Little worſhip in the court is great honor in the towne.</note> the which happeneth ſeldome in the court &amp; in great cities and townes: for there he ſhall ſée other goe before him, more trim and more braue and gorgious then he, as well in credite as in riches, as well in the houſe as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the houſe. And <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> ſayd to this purpoſe that he had rather bée the firſt in a village, then the ſecond in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor in <hi>Rome.</hi> For ſuch men as haue high hartes and mindes, and baſe fortune, it ſhould be to them much better to liue in the village with honor, then in the court ouerthrowen and abated, and out of fauor. The difference betwéene the tariyng or abidyng in a litle place and a great place, is that in the litle places are founde much people poore and née<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, of whom men may take compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and in the great place many riche men whereby enuy is noriſhed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities that come by dwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling in the vil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lage.</note>Another commoditie in the village is, that euery man enioyeth in quiet
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3663:28"/> and peace ſuch as God hath geuen him, without to haue ſuch to come to their houſes, that ſhall conſtrayne them to make extraordinary expe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes, or to haue his wife ſeduced, or his daughters defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. The occaſions to doo euil be put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by reaſon that he is occupied in the mainteining of his houſholde, in tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his ſonnes &amp; chaſtening of hys ſeruauntes. He liueth confirmed to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and not to his opinion: and liues hopyng to dye &amp; not as he that loueth to liue euer. In the village,<note place="margin">We ought to liue, as dying.</note> thou ſhalt not care for good lodging, nor for looking to thy Horſes and Mules, nor for the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of ſuch thinges as they ſhall cary. Thou ſhalt not heare the crying of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, the plaintes of the ſtuardes of the houſe, the babling of the Cookes, nor thou ſhalt feare Iudges nor Iuſtices, leaſt they ſhuld be to ſore againſt thée. And that which is much better, thou ſhalt haue no craftie knaues to bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guyle thée, nor women to betraye thée.</p>
               <p>Another benefite of the village
<pb facs="tcp:3663:29"/> is this, that he ſhall haue time enough to al thinges that he will do, ſo that the time be well ſpent, time enough to ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, time to viſite his frendes, time to go a hunting, and layſer when he liſt to eate his meat: the which layſer cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers commonly haue not,<note place="margin">Courtiers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>dom leyſure to eate their meate.</note> for aſmuche as they employe the moſte part of their time in making of ſhiftes to playe the courtier, or to ſpeake more plainely, to wepe and lament, in ſuch ſorte that one may ſay of them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour <hi>Auguſtus</hi> ſaid of a <hi>Roman</hi> a great buſie broker the ſame day that hée dyed. I wonder ſaid he, ſéeyng the tyme failed him to chop and to chaunge, how hée could now finde layſer to dye? Another commoditie of the village is this, thoſe that be dwellers there maye goe alone from place to place without to be noted to fall from grauitie, they néede no Mule nor Horſe with a foote clothe,<note place="margin">The countrey lyfe, requireth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o great train</note> nor page to wayte of my lorde, or damoſell to waite vpon my lady. And that were ſcornefull to do in the court alone And without daunger one may walke
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3663:29"/> from neighbor to neighbor, and from land to land, and not thereby miniſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part of his honor.</p>
               <p>Another benefite is,<note place="margin">The ruſtique life requireth no ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptuous aparrell.</note> that men may go whether they will, clothed ſimply with a ſtaffe in his hande, a ſwearde by his ſide, or hacbut in his necke, and if he be weary of pounſed hoſen, let h m weare ſtoppes, if he be a colde let him take his furred gowne for all is one there. A good gentleman dwelling in the village and hauing a good coate of cloath, an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Spaniſh cloke on his back, a paire of lether ſhooes, goeth as well trimmed to the church as doth my Lord the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier to the court with his gowne furde with Marters or Sables. A man of the village of what ſorte ſoeuer he be, is in as good caſe, that rydeth to market or to the faier to make prouiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for his houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde vpon a mare or a nagge,<note place="margin">A poore plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is far bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter than a rich and honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble extorcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, though he be in the court</note> as a lord of the courte is at Iuſtes vpon a great courſer trapped with golde. And (when all is ſayd) better is the poore plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man on a poore aſſe, liuing as he ſhould, then the rich man well horſed, pilling
<pb facs="tcp:3663:30"/> and doyng extorcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to pore honeſt men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>The .vj Chapiter. ¶That in the village the dayes ſeeme more long, and the ayer more clere and better. And the houſes more eaſy and reſtful than in the court.</head>
               <p>ENſuing ſtill the commodities of the village, wée ought not to forget that he which dwelles there, among other thinges hath commoditie of good corne, and conſequently good bread: contrary to this, in the court, &amp; ſpecially in great townes they haue breade for the moſt part euil baked or euil leauened, or not leauened at all, &amp; the cauſe is, foraſmuch as in the townes ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there lacketh good corne, or good corne milles to grinde the corne, &amp; holſome water, whereby often hath come among them great death.</p>
               <p>Another commoditie in the village is this, the which I prayſe much, hée
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3663:30"/> that dwelles there, may practiſe and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in mo thinges and better imploy the tyme then in the court or in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great townes: in which places it behoueth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble, to ſay litle, to be ful of re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenging &amp; enuyous, a treader of ſtones and pauemontes, &amp; muſt vſe grauitie, and ſeldome to come out of his houſe, and inceſſantly be graue. O half a God, that dwelles in the village where libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally one may ſpeake what he wil, and ieſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his neighbours before his gates and his window. And this may hée doe without euer to chaunge or to léeſe any of his meane auctoritie.</p>
               <p>Another co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie is in the village,<note place="margin">Health more aboundeth in villages than in great tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; courtes.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dwel there, be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out compariſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more healthfull &amp; leſſe ſicke then in the cities and in the court, becauſe in the great townes the houſes be more high, and the ſtreates narower, &amp; more cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, which is the cauſe that the ayre is corrupt and makes men very euill at eaſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> village the houſes ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d more at large, the men more better diſpoſed, the ayre better, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſunne more clere, the
<pb facs="tcp:3663:31"/> earth more ſwéete, the priuate goodes or commons better ruled without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and the exerciſe more pleaſant, and the company much better: And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all thinges the thoughtes leſſer, and the paſtyme more great.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Young Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oians, and old ſickneſſes are not in villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</note>Another commoditie in the village is, that there are no young Phiſicians, nor olde ſicknes: And contrary to this, the courtier is conſtrained there to part his goodes in fower partes, the one part to flatterers, the other to men of lawe, another to Pottecaries, &amp; the fowerth to the Phiſicians. O wel fortunate vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, foraſmuch as in thée, ſeldome or neuer is the French pocks named,<note place="margin">French pocks dwelleth not in the village as it doth in the courte.</note> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the paucy nor yet the goute: fewe or none there knoweth what is a Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lep, a Pyll, a Sirup, or a Thyſan, nor no ſodain ſickenes. What will ye that I ſhall ſay more of the village? And if it were not, but that for neceſſitie, they are compelled to builde there litle pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie houſes, ye ſhould ſcant finde one of them that knew what to do with mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſtones? And ſometime they are
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3663:31"/> very well pleaſed with cabons made of ſmall ſtickes well faſtened together.</p>
               <p>Another commoditie of the village is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the dayes there ſéeme to be more long, and they are better imployed, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are eyther in the court or in the great townes, foraſmuch as the yeares paſſe away there or one be ware, and the dayes without any enoying of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And howbeit that the ſportes and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures be more in the village then in the townes, yet ſo it is that one day ſhall ſéeme lenger there then ſhall a moneth in the court: and the reaſon is, for that the village is happy and fortunate, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as there the Sunne ſéemes to make a more longer day, the morning is ready to ſhow, and the night ſlow to come.<note place="margin">Tyme ſpent in the court ſod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nly vani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſheth away.</note> Scarcely one can perceiue the dayes ſlyde away in the court: In the village if it be perceiued, it is beſtowed with honeſt buſines, which cannot bee done in the court.</p>
               <p>In the village alſo is much more plentie of wood then in other places:<note place="margin">Vittailes and all prouiſion is more plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious in the villages than in the court.</note> hay, ſtrawe, Otes much better cheape
<pb facs="tcp:3663:32"/> then in good townes. Alſo in the village a man is at libertie to eate his meate where he will, &amp; when he will, &amp; with whom he will: but in the court they eat late, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meat euil dreſſed &amp; colde, &amp; with out ſauor, &amp; that which is worſt of all, for the moſt part, he muſt eate with his enemies, where as the good felowes of the village liue at their pleaſures and without ſuſpicion, keeping their thrée good faſhions that belongeth to good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt,<note place="margin">Three good faſhions in the countrey.</note> that is, firſt he earneth his meat, next that he eateth his meate merely, and thyrdly hée eateth with good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
               <p>Another commoditie is, that the huſbandman of the village hath how to occupy himſelfe and how to be me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which the courtier, nor the citizen hath not, that hath enemies enough to feare, and fewe frendes to companye withall.<note place="margin">Recreations of the village.</note> O recreacion pleaſaunt of the village, to fiſhe with nettes, and with hookes, to catch birdes with lyme, to hunt with dogges, to catch Conies with Ferrets, &amp; hayes, to ſhoote in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſbow
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3663:32"/> and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hacbut at ſtockdoues, at Mallar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp; at patriges: &amp; ſée folkes labor in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vynes, raiſe diches, amend hedges, to ieſt with the auncient laborers, All theſe pleaſures haue they of the villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, wheras the courtiers and citezens deſire it, and cannot haue it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>The .vij. Chapiter. ¶That commonly the inhabitaunts of the villages be more happy then courtiers.</head>
               <p>ANother commoditie of the village is, that they doe féele the trauayles leſſe on the working day, and reioyce merely on the holy day:<note place="margin">Holidayes ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed of courtiers.</note> where the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier continually vexed with weightie and troubleous affaires, neuer knoweth when it is holiday. O village, it is not ſo in thée, whereas on the feaſtfull day the clerke ceaſeth not to tolle the bell, to make cleane y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, to make ready for ſeruice, the people honeſtlye appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relled, the feaſtes commaunded to bée obſerued, the curate preacheth the
<pb facs="tcp:3663:33"/> goſpel, and after dinner they make me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with a thouſande honeſt paſtymes. In the great townes the holidayes are knowen when the wiues go gay, when they ſléepe long in the morning,<note place="margin">True noates of vanitie in Cities and Courtes.</note> when they play after dinner: and generally when they conſume the day in volupte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes and vanities.</p>
               <p>Another commoditie is this, that where the courtiers vſe to eate fleſhe and corrupt veniſon &amp; wilde foule that is long kept, they of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> village haue their meate freſh and freſh, tender and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome,<note place="margin">The dyet of the Countrey.</note> and as one may ſay, in good ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: that is, houſedoues, Partrige, pullettes, Stockdoues, Woodcockes, Feſauntes, fatte Capons, Conyes, Hares, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable victayl of all ſortes. And o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and beſides this, to their great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntage they haue ſheepe that beareth wol to cloath them, good mutton to eat, dong to make fatte their grounde, and Kyddes and Goates alſo, with Oxen to labor in the plough, and kyne to milke and make butter &amp; chéeſe: and hogges to make bacon of, Coltes for to noriſh,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3663:33"/> and Horſes for to ſerue them and for to ſell when néede requireth. And another priuelege of the village is this, that the good ſhall be honoured for a good man, and the vnthriftie perſon knowen as he is, which is not ſo in the court,<note place="margin">The parcialli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the court</note> for there is no man prayſed for that he deſerueth to be praiſed, but becauſe he hath aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and riches.</p>
               <p>O how much is the wiſe man hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the village for his wiſedome and good counſail? how many tymes is he thanked and how many preſentes hath be:<note place="margin">The thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of the huſbandman.</note> If parcaſe one of his neighbors haue any good fruit in his garden, a good me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, a good pear, or a good muſcadell grape, gladlye they will preſent him therewith, as to him that hath deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it.</p>
               <p>Another preuilege of the village is this, that euery man may marrye his daughters to his equalles and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, that thereby dayly hee may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue both pleaſure &amp; ſeruice, the which the courtiers cannot doe that marry his daughters ſo farre from them, that
<pb facs="tcp:3663:34"/> for the moſt parte they lament them or they ſée them. O happy inhabitor in the village that findes at his gate huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes for his daughters, and wyues for his ſonnes. He maryeth them nygh to him that he may eaſly ſée his ſonnes in lawe,<note place="margin">The huſband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of his children by their preſence.</note> his litle nephues and his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie: he is beloued of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſuccoured in his affaires, ſerued &amp; noriſhed in his ſicknes, &amp; great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort to him in his age</p>
               <p>Another commoditie is, that they are not to much carefull nor yet ireful or enuious: which commoditie they of the court and the citizens litle taſte or enioye: for the courtier many times lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth money, when his greate affayres ſhuld be brought to paſſe. I ſay therfore O happy man of the village, that néeds not to goe at ten of the clocke to the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice to beg counſail, to ſpeake fayre to the vſher, to wait vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the preſident, and make <hi>flectamus ienua</hi> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawyer,<note place="margin">The courtier croucheth and flattereth for aduantage.</note> and flatter the king &amp; his counſail, and the Magiſtrate: but hath in ſteade of theſe Idolatries for a happy ſolace, the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites of nature &amp; the paſtimes therof, to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3663:34"/> heare the ſhéepe blete y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Bulles to bray,<note place="margin">The delights of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey.</note> the Horſe to neyh, the Nitingales to ſing, the Thruſhes to warble, the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets to mynſe their ſonges, dogges to run, Lambes to leape, Kyddes to gam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolde, and ſee the Pekockes ſet vp their tailes like a whele, He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to kecle, kockes to crow, &amp; a thouſand kynde of beaſtes and birdes play and ſporte.</p>
               <p>Another commoditie is, that in the village one may be there more vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and leſſe vicious then in the courte or in the great cities, &amp; the reaſon is, for that in great companyes we ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menly finde a M. that kéepe men from good doyng, &amp; .x.M. that will moue vs to doe euil. And in the village euery man ſanctifieth the Sabboth day,<note place="margin">The Sabbath better hallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed in the countrey th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n in the citie.</note> keepeth the feaſtes, heareth the ſermons, &amp; by thys meanes with great labor worketh his ſoule health aſſiſted by grace. Wherefore the village is to be praiſed for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the occaſions of euil, &amp; of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction are not ſo plentiful &amp; practiſed there, as they are in the courte and in good townes, no cookes houſes to make
<pb facs="tcp:3663:35"/> them licorous: nor there are no greate eſtates wherby enuy ſhould ariſe: there is no chopping nor chaunging by vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:<note place="margin">Vſury, whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther euels, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey as in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</note> whores to quarell and fight for, nor courtiers to torney in armure, nor wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton and lewde places to corrupt youth withall: nor Iuſtices to feare them, ye (and that beſt of all is) no couetouſnes which ſhould ſwalow vp and deuour them.</p>
               <p>Another priuilege there is, that their one may well gather ſome good,<note place="margin">Prugallitie in the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, and prodigal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie in the court.</note> &amp; ſpend much leſſe then in the court. For euery man knowes well what exceſſiue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences are accuſtomed to be waſted in the court, and ſpecially in theſe dayes, that the great apparelling of bankettes is ſuch that they be well worthy to bee reformed. O peaceable peyſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts which néedes not the tapettes of <hi>Flaunders,</hi> lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen cloath of <hi>Holland,</hi> ſiluer plate, gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes imbrodered, Parcement lace purfilde, nor yet cariage, Mulettes, var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lettes to conduct them, nor other ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous attyre: but contrary in ſtéede of that, is contented with a litle houſhold
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3663:35"/> well ruled, with a groſſe table &amp; a fewe plaine ſtooles to eate his meate vpon, with diſhes of Peuter, and a mattres for to ſléepe on, two gownes, one for ſommer, another for winter, one gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the ſtable, one varlet, one cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berer to doe him ſeruice: As much hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py is a gentleman and as much hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with his litle company in his houſe in the village, as is a rich Lord in the court with his pride, &amp; ruffling traine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>The .viij Chapiter. ¶That in princes courtes the cuſtome and vſe is to ſpeake of God and liue after the worlde.</head>
               <p>IN the Court, euen as there is no rigorous iuſtice, no father y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chaſtiſeth his ſonne, no frende that correcteth one the other, none that loueth his neighbor,<note place="margin">Libertie to do euil, is in the court.</note> no bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop nor curate that gouerneth wel his ſhéepe, nor teacheth them after the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell: So he that is by nature good, hath
<pb facs="tcp:3663:36"/> great libertie to be naught. In the court if one will be an adulterer, he ſhal haue fellowes. If he wil be a quareller, hée ſhall haue helpe,<note place="margin">Fellow furthe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rers of wicked<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes in the court.</note> and that with ſuch as will drawe their ſwordes. If he be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to banqueting, euery where hée ſhall finde gluttons, If he wil manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; ſhamefully lye, he ſhall finde com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions ready that will approue hys lyes: If he will ſteale, he ſhal finde them that wil inſtruct him many wayes ther to: If he will playe, there are ſo many cardes &amp; ſo many diſe,<note place="margin">Cardes and Diſe are plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull in the court.</note> that it is ſhame to ſee it: If one wil be falſly forſworne, he ſhall finde them that will geue mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for forſwearing: Fynally, if he wil vtterly geue himſelf to doe euil, in the court he ſhall ſée perfect examples. To the court reſorteth men of diuers naci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſome for buſines, ſome to pleade or to ſerue,<note place="margin">After what manner, ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers come ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted in the court.</note> or to ſhewe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, which perſons to bring themſelues acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted are forced to folow the ſeruauntes of ſuche as be in auctoritie, to flatter them, and ſpeake fayre to them: and to folowe the companyes and felowſhip
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3663:36"/> of the taberers, the Pypers, the Muſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, the flatterers &amp; mery ieſters, and at the ende become God knowes poore and néedy gentlemen, in ſuch wiſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by very neceſſitie they be compelled to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d rewardes, newyeres giftes, and new apparell. And yet to theſe euill fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, they which geue any good thing, geue it rather to get the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues a name to be called full of magnificence, then for any charitie at all.</p>
               <p>In the Court, fortune is inconſtant,<note place="margin">Fortune is in conſtant in the court.</note> in that ſhée promiſeth, and yet more in that which ſhe geueth, for at one inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, where one ryſeth, another falleth, one is borne, another dyeth: he is auaunced that is vnknowen, and the faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt forgotten, he that will abyde is not receiued, but he that will runne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way is taken in: fooles are beleued and wiſemen belyed, opinions be folowed and reaſon let paſſe. With theſe things and other ſemblable thynges that we aſſaye and ſee in Courtes of pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, euery manne maye bee aſſured that fortune wyll knocke at hys
<pb facs="tcp:3663:37"/> doore, though for the moſt part the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers finde ſoner their graue then any good fortune, and ſpecially ſuch that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour to be diſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of a good houſe, go to the court to bragge,<note place="margin">Some Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers are me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter for the cart than for the ſpeare.</note> and yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe are ſo fooliſhe and ignoraunt, that it may be ſaid they are more méete for the cart then for the ſpeare, ſo that they ſerue in concluſion to be a daliance to the mockers and ieſters. And one great miſchief is in the court, that there is euer hatred amonges the princes, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy among familiars,<note place="margin">Contencion among cour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiers.</note> contencio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among officers and with their felowes. And among theſe there neuer lacketh med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers &amp; buſie bodyes, which profite more thereby, then ſome doctor of diuinitie doeth by preaching. In the court all is ſuffered,<note place="margin">All ſortes of men reſort to the court.</note> all is diſſembled withall, all is inconſtant, and all ſortes deſyre there to liue: and foraſmuch as all deſire there to liue, it is impoſſible but there muſt be lyers, players, ſlaunderers, &amp; a great nomber of naughtie perſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Euery euil parſon hath his mate.</note>In the court the euill foloweth the euil: The brauler findes one to braule
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3663:37"/> withal: The adulterer one that he may ſinne withall: The théefe a companion and receiuer: The ſophiſter a babler: and all rekened together, one ready to deceiue another.</p>
               <p>In the court euery man prayſeth and commendeth himſelfe of holy purpoſes and noble thoughtes. One ſayth he will withdrawe himſelfe from the courte. And another ſayeth he will forget hys ſuites.<note place="margin">Wordes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out deedes in the court.</note> Another ſayeth he will quenche enemitie. And when they haue all ſayd, all is but wordes, for the heart thinketh of nothing els but of the world. None knoweth there the one the other: The men of armes go without harnys: The prelates without their rotchettes: The The prieſt without his porteaues:<note place="margin">Confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and diſorder in the court.</note> The daughter without her mother: The wife without her huſband: The clerke without his bookes: The theefe without a ſpye: The glutton from table to ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. The vacabond from place to place, and the baude from doore to doore, and from harlot to harlot. In the court there be biſhoppes to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme curates, to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe
<pb facs="tcp:3663:38"/> and chaunge names: For he that is glorious gay, they name him honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,<note place="margin">Vice is called vertue.</note> he that ſpendes all, full of magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, the cowarde wyſe, the valiaunt ouer hardy, the foole ioyous, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyſe an hipocrite, the malicious ſubtle, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcoffer eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the adulterer Amorous, the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous meſurable, and he that talketh litle, a foole &amp; an ignoraunt perſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>The .ix. Chapiter. ¶In the court fewe amend, but many waxe worſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Wiſedome without for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune profiteth little in the court.</note>IN the court it profites litle, men to be wiſe, vnleſſe they be fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, foraſmuch as good ſeruice is ſoone forgotten: frendes ſoone faile, &amp; enemies augme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nobilitie do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forget it ſelf, ſcience is forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie diſpiſed, trueth cloked &amp; hid, and good counſaill refuſed. The beſt myne and the richeſt Alcumet that the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier may haue,<note place="margin">Fauor is the Courtiers ſtaffe, to leane vnto.</note> is to haue wynde at wil to ſaile with, that is, to be in fauor with
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3663:38"/> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be fauoured, till fortune laugh vpon him: for the condicions and faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of entertainment chaungeth dayly and hourely. To proue this true, <hi>Plato</hi> needs not to ſpeak, nor <hi>Cicero</hi> to ſwear, foraſmuch as afore our eyes we ſee the foole become wyſe, the meeke, become proude, the ſober a glutton,<note place="margin">Wiſe men tranſformed into fooles.</note> the pacient a brauler, and the deuout an euil chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man.</p>
               <p>In the court it is a great buſines and trauaile for to finde vertue,<note place="margin">Vertue is hard to fynde in the court.</note> and greater daunger and perill to kéepe it. Is not humilitie loſt among them that be in honor, or pacience among wrong doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, or abſtinence among gluttons, or chaſtitie amonges women, or reſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monges buſines, or charitie amonges euil willers, or peace amonges ſedici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, or ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce amongeſt bablers, or good witte: where is ſo much folly? In the court no man is content, euery man co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth,<note place="margin">No man is contented in the court.</note> eyther becauſe the kyng ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him nought, or becauſe the prince helpeth him not, or that one or other is euer betwixt him and home: He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints
<pb facs="tcp:3663:39"/> of the porter he wil not let him in: of the treaſurer that he payeth hym not: of his crediture which taketh away his goodes: or of one or other that doeth him wrong in the court. If one reade a letter of pleaſure, he ſhall reade an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth of diſpleaſure. The wyfe ſhall write to her huſband and pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im for to come home, that he may marry hys daughters being of age, or that his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren be diſobedient, that his frendes hath forſaken him, and that by ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude they render euil for good, werines doth aſſayle her on all ſides, that her te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauntes call her to the lawe, that hys goodes be ſpent? ſurely hée ſhall heare ſuch newes, ſo that for two grotes that he geueth to the bearer of the letters, he would gladly haue geuen more to haue hard no ſuch newes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Euils ineui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in the court.</note>In the court a man doth many things by neceſſitie, that to dye for it he would not doe in his houſe: he dynes &amp; ſuppes with his enemies, he ſpeakes with him that he neuer knewe nor pleaſeth hym not, defendes him that helpes him not,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3663:39"/> foloweth him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honoureth not him, le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds to him that payeth him not, diſſembles with him that doeth him iniury, &amp; tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes to him that beguiles him.</p>
               <p>O vnhappy and ſorowfull courtier if by chaunce he growe to be a poore man,<note place="margin">The miſeries of the court.</note> no man will ſuccour him, and if he fall ſicke no man viſites him, and if he dye he is incontinent forgotten: if he be ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous no man commendes him, and if he be out of creadite no man regardes him. In the court there is nothing more rare nor more deare to recouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, nor more eaſy to fynde then the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundaunce of thrée maner of people. That is of tale bringers, of flatterers, and of liers.<note place="margin">Three ſortes of people plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull in the court.</note> The liers deceiue the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. The flatterers the rich men. The tale bringers, thoſe that be in fauour. The women, deceiue the men. The co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſnes, the olde men. The pompe the prelates The auaricious, the prieſtes. The libertie the religious, ambicion, the preſumptuous, the wiſe confidence in men, and all they ioyned together be deceiued by fortune.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3663:40"/>
               <p>In the court men employe the tyme ſo euil that from the time the courtier do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth aryſe,<note place="margin">Newes is ſtill inquired for in the court.</note> till he goe to bed, he occupieth himſelf about nothing but in aſkyng of newes, ietting about the ſtreetes, write letters, ſpeake of the warres, entertein them that be in fauour, counſail with baudes, make as he were in loue and léeſe alwayes the tyme. In the court more then in any other place the things are ſlow. For one riſes late, and worſt of all amendes his life late. All thinges there is variable and chaungeable and inconſtaunt.<note place="margin">Alteration of ſtates.</note> The eſtates chaunge, The litle aſſend, the great fall. The widowes there be marde: The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried be defamed: The maydens bée ſhamed: The good ſpirites be dulled: The valiaunt becommes cowardes: The prelates waxe worſe and worſe: The ſciences are forgotten: The young léeſe their time: The olde vndone: This is the courtiers life, He is not worthy to be a courtier vnleſſe he bée in debte and owethe to the draper for cloath,<note place="margin">Debt becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth a courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</note> to the Merſer for ſilk, to the taylor for the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3663:40"/> making of his apparel, to the goldſmith for iewels for my Lord y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courtiers la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, to the Iudges for the diſputyng of proceſſes, to the ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes for wages, to their hoſtes for their ſpence. There is to much euil counſail, euen ſuch as is more then the halfe way leadyng to damnacion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>The .x. Chapiter. ¶That a man cannot liue in the court, without to trouble himſelfe or ſome other.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> Courtier doeth many things,<note place="margin">Faſhion is the rule of the court.</note> more for to ſay, I doo as other men do, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for any néede he hath ſo to doe. He ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kettes with euery man becauſe he will not be called an hypocrite, Playes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would not be named a nigard, and companies with many, becauſe hée wil not be named a ſolitarima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; geues to raſcal &amp; naughtie perſons becauſe he would not be euil ſaid of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">All men ſeeke for a name.</note> A man in
<pb facs="tcp:3663:41"/> the court is full of penſiuenes and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: For it is trueth that it is appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pried to them of nature that followes the court, to bée inceſſantly tormented. He muſt praiſe his felowes, diſprayſe ſtraungers, and looke vnto them that do euil, and blame them that doe wel, and ſpend at large with his felowes, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the enemies ſpare not his owne proper life: And all this muſt he doo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he will not be diſprayſed. In the court commonly one profeſſeth to wait of one maiſter,<note place="margin">A courtier ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth many maiſters.</note> but for all that, he muſt ſerue at the taile of diuers other lordes. O broken heart of the poore courtier that muſt néeds ſerue ſuch as knoweth him not, and make reuerence to them that deſerue not to haue it, and muſt ſay to my maiſter the officer an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth tymes a day, Sir and if it pleaſe you. And he ſhall anſwere when I am at leyſer:<note place="margin">Euery officer in the court lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth for reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</note> tary a whyle at the doore. And yet we muſt call him maiſter y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues it no more then the hangman that ſtrangles a man with a halter. O what pitie is it to ſee a poore ſuiter in his née<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3663:41"/> buſines folow the kyng from towne to towne euil noriſhed,<note place="margin">Suters which follow after the court haue a colde ſute.</note> and worſe lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged? The king hath buſines, the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailer is defe, the Almoner hath no ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and he that thou knoweſt hath no eyes:<note place="margin">Money ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth frendes.</note> And without money &amp; extreame paine, the fiue wittes of nature be lame.</p>
               <p>In the court, albeit that one hath no enemies which is ſeldome ſéene, yet is it truth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many tymes his owne frends put him out of quiet, foraſmuche as if the courtier will take reſt in hys lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng, they grunt at him becauſe he will not goe ſee his frendes, &amp; prouoke hym to goe folow the princes in the courte, ſaying, that the raſcal and the varlettes mocke at him that he goeth not thether and ſhewe himſelf frée and liberal: and when he is ariued at the court, which is a naturall enemy to reſt,<note place="margin">The court is a natural ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to reſt.</note> and a deſire of nouelles, then muſt he chaunge, as doeth the <hi>Egipcian,</hi> which euery day ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a new countrey, a newe lodgyng, new apparell, and conuerſacions, buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and faſhions of men. Lo my frende and the reader of this: This is the life
<pb facs="tcp:3663:42"/> of the courtier as it is here deſcribed: and alſo of hym that liueth in the vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage the which ſayd life of the peyſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſhall be much practiſed of many, and choſen of a fewe, becauſe that euery man readeth bookes enough &amp; the more he readeth the leſſe he chaungeth of his euil cuſtomes. And to call to reaſon why it is ſo, it foloweth that the court of princes is good but for two maner of men,<note place="margin">The court is good for two ſortes of men.</note> for them that be in fauor, and for the you<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g which be yet of a weak iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And thoſe that be in fauor, and doe wayte dayly, ſée themſelues ſo rich, ſo feared, and ſo well accompanied that they féele not the payne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> court. And the pleaſure they gette thereby makes them for concluſion forget themſelues, yet notwithſtanding for all thys,<note place="margin">The happieſt courtiers are not without trouble.</note> it is impoſſible but that their braynes muſt be troubled, becauſe they be to much oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied, for their houſes are to ful of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, their eares full of lyes, their toun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues to much troubled with anſwering of euery man, their heartes to muche preſſed to ayde and help them that they
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3663:42"/> would helpe, and other. And finally the greater in auctoritie and credite they bée, ye ſhall ſee them the more penſiue and the more aſtonied, and for the moſt part ſooner complaine then reioyce: but commaund who commaund will, haue credite who will, the truth is,<note place="margin">There is no pleaſure with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſt be ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned therewith.</note> none can take pleaſure of his goods, without ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt reſt. Beſide this, thoſe which bée ſayd to be in fauor, are euer in feare to be put down from their auctoritie: And by that meanes are in continuall dread and torment, the which is an enemye mortall to quiet and reſt. And the yong in like caſe (as I haue ſaid) that be with out iudgement and blynded in vyces, do not know nor ſée the incommodities of the court, nor care, neyther for fauor nor honor, but bounden and drownde in volupteouſnes and vices, paſſe the better parte of their dayes in the ſchoole that is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worth, vnder the maiſter of pardicion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:3663:43"/>
               <head>The xi. Chapiter. ¶That in the court thoſe that be graue are praiſed and wel eſteemed, and the other that doe the contrary not regarded.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Courtier ſhuld not acquaint himſelf with vaine and ydle perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, that he be not reputed to be ſuch as hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panieth withall. For it had not béen enough for him to ſay he muſt néedes doe there as other doe, and diſſemble as other diſſembles. Neither behoueth it him not to cloke his naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie doyng, in goyng ſecretely to ſuch as be naught, for why? the wittes of the courtiers are ſo fine, that they knowe not onely what one ſayeth but what he thinketh. There is neither little nor great, but men ſpye him whether he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, from whence he commeth, &amp; where he abideth, with whom he talketh, in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3663:43"/> whom he talketh, in whom he truſteth, and what he will doe, ſo well, that the curtens may hyde a perſon, but to hyde the viſes of the courtiers is impoſſible. The courtier alſo ought not to brag and crake that thinges ſhalbe as he would, he may not preſume to ſpeake to the kyng and require audience as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf luſt: for he that foloweth the court muſt be as one that hath no mouth to ſpeake, nor handes to be auenged with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,<note place="margin">Little loue is in the court.</note> beyng well aſſured that there is no more loue in the court, then are clothes vpon a bare horſe. For he that is in the court, and is not armed with pacience, it had béen much better for him not to haue come out of his countrey, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a quareller and ſedicious felow,<note place="margin">Pacience be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to a courtier.</note> in the court he ſhalbe hated, and paradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture baniſhed from thence, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his returning ſhalbe to his vtter ſhame.</p>
               <p>Malice and diſpleaſures take often an end in the village, but in the court is alwayes an ouerplus of them. What is the cauſe? Fortune I ſay: which hath the rule ouer them who count her for a
<pb facs="tcp:3663:44"/> goddeſſe,<note place="margin">Fortune is feared more than there is cauſe.</note> which is more feared of a foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh opinion, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for any power ſhe hath ouer men.</p>
               <p>The courtier alſo ought not to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to that which his ſenſualitie requireth, but to that which reaſon doth perſuade him vnto,<note place="margin">Reaſon ought to rule all men.</note> foraſmuch as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des more then néedes, and the other contentes him with leſſe then he hath. Foraſmuch then as in the court, there are ſo many tables to glutto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny new found playes to play at, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny quarelles to fight for, ſo many mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to pleade, there is no cauſe to mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile if the ſage be cheriſhed, and the diſſolute perſon blamed. The good man within the court, is as a nutte within the ſhale,<note place="margin">A good man in the court is as a nut with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſhale.</note> and mary within the bone, and a perle within the cokle, and a roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the thornes. I doe not ſay reader, for the qualitie and qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>titie of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of the court, that all be vicious that be there: God forbid that it ſo ſhould bee, but when I call to remembraunce we be all mortall men, I thinke it in maner impoſſible to ariue ſafe into the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3663:44"/> porte, among ſo many <hi>Sillas</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribdes.</hi> Ye will ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the wily and the ſubtle perſon there waxeth riche, and that the great ſummes of money bee there: I confeſſe it, &amp; I would ſay your ſaying ſhould bée good if they that were of the beſt knowledge and the moſt ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous nomber were auaunced for their prudence, as the other be by hazard and chaunce or by theft,<note place="margin">Vertues re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes excell the rewardes of fortune.</note> for the rewarde of vertue, is not lyke the reward of fortune.</p>
               <p>Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the courtier ought not to geue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentes, nor lightly take, for why?<note place="margin">Preſentes and giftes howe they ought to be geuen.</note> for to geue him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deſerues it not, there lackes wiſedome. And to receiue of him that one ought not, is a thing but vile.</p>
               <p>Who y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wil exerciſe liberalitie,<note place="margin">Liberallitie.</note> ought to conſider what he geueth, &amp; to whom he geueth: for it ſhould be but folly to geue that which one may not, and that which he himſelf néedes. And one ought to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the tyme and the end and the ſeaſon, and wherfore he geueth. And if the courtier geue ſomethyng ouer libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie &amp; without iuſt cauſe of reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb facs="tcp:3663:45"/> of him which is out of creadite, and in the tyme that he beginneth to declyne, is not then the gift euil imployed? is it not to be lamented that one geues ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to the flatterer to tell ſome feined or lying tales,<note place="margin">Giftes ill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed.</note> or a ieſter to make them laugh, or to a common lyer to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> talke, or to a pleaſaunt felow to inuent a lye, rather then to a truſtie ſeruaunt that hath all the dayes of his life deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to haue thanke for his good ſeruice? Yet for all this, myne entencion is not to perſuade great men that they ſhould not geue to all men: but I ſay the true ſeruauntes ought to be preferred, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is more méete that their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice ſhould be rewarded, then the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentes of ſtraungers conſidered.</p>
               <p>When a man geueth to ſtraungers, the ſeruauntes ſéeing the ſame drawe backe: yée may be aſſured that they not only murmure at that which is geuen, but alſo accuſe him of his vnge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle déed, and become a mortall enemy to hym that the thing is geuen vnto.<note place="margin">Giftes bynde the giuer.</note> The giftes makes a man much ſubiect that recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3663:45"/> them, for aſſoone as any man doth take of another an horſe or a gowne, or ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſit with him at his table, he bindes himſelfe thereby to beare him fauour, to defend his quarel, to keepe him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, to take his parte, and to loue that that he loueth. And reaſon will, that ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens one féeleth profite of another that he be not vnkynde, howbeit let a man beware to binde himſelfe ſo much vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the will of other men, that he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by forgetteth his owne honeſtie. Many young children diſcended of an honeſt houſe goe to the court &amp; take with them a good parte of their goodes &amp; conſume the ſame playing, eating, and drinking,<note place="margin">Prodigall ſonnes.</note> and vſing baudry and adultery vnder colour of learning their behauior: and reſorte to the great mennes houſes, to no other intent, but to be much made of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> where they take a great repaſt, and afterward ſo playe the young wanton fooles, that they ſpende rent, honor and all. And when the purſe is flat,<note place="margin">Newes hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</note> their of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice is to go all the day in the ſtréetes to the churches and to the palaice to aſke
<pb facs="tcp:3663:46"/> newes and tidynges, only to pype out lyes and fables at the Lordes boordes, and all for to goe ſcot free. And there is a ſorte of young men in the court, yea I may ſay to you, of thoſe that haue bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, that neither haue maiſter nor en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainers, that as ſoone as a ſtraunger commeth to the court, ſtraightwayes they boorde him, ſaying that they will ſhewe him the faſhions and maners of the court,<note place="margin">Faſhion tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers.</note> the pleaſures of the palaices, the maner how to kéepe him from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptfull felowes, and to entertain yong gentlewomen. And thus the new come courtier that is yet a foole, in the mean ſeaſon ſhalbe handled in ſuch wiſe that now goeth a gowne, now a coate, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tyme a horſe, and ſometyme purſe and all. And there is another ſorte of men in the court that buſieth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with ſo great auctoritie and with ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle wit, that after they haue vſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of ſome great Lord, they wil ſend him a letter by their page, ſaying they be poore gentlemen,<note place="margin">Poore gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhifters.</note> kynſfolke to ſome great men, and that they be there ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3663:46"/> for ſome office, and that they haue a payment in hand, wherefore they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire him to lende him a certaine ſum of money: And yet are they in no ſuch neceſſitie, but onely to get ſomewhat, eyther to buye a gay coate, or a horſe, or to kéepe a whore.</p>
               <p>There is another ſorte of falſe and beggerly courtiers, the which after they be once vſed to the court, they goe from church to church to aſke for Gods ſake,<note place="margin">Roagues.</note> ſaying they be poore ſuiters &amp; that they loue better to begge then to robbe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending themſelues to the prieſtes to beg for them on the poore pariſheners when they preach, and ſo take agaynſt reaſon the good y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> poore men ſhuld haue.</p>
               <p>There is another ſorte of haunters in the court,<note place="margin">Table hau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ters</note> that goe from one houſe to another of the great eſtates and Lords, counterfaiting to bée diligent ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, flatteryng the ſteward, the butler, and the cooke, and liue of that which is left of the dinners, and goe their wayes with theyr pockettes and their ſléeues full of meate for to ſuppe withall. And
<pb facs="tcp:3663:47"/> there is another maner of ſorte that go two and two, and thrée and three toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a morning to ſpy and ſee if there be any thing euil kepte,<note place="margin">Picking pilſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and with that to looke and to prye if a ſword or a Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh cloke, or a purſe be fallen aſide, if there bée, they ſing in a mery note this is <hi>pro nobis.</hi> Other there be that for to conduict and defende a whore when the court remoues (as one may ſaye more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ruffians) they liue of the gaine of the miſerable woman.<note place="margin">Apple ſqueeres</note> Another hath falſe diſe, falſe marked cardes for to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the innocentes, winne their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,<note place="margin">Cogging ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſters.</note> and léeſe their owne ſoules. And there lackes not in the court old wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and wrinckled trottes that after their harueſt is paſt,<note place="margin">Bawdes.</note> cloake the ſinnes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and beguile thoſe that be chaſt and vndermine ſuche as be married, hurte their neighbours, ſell mayde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to whore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome for luker, and doe noriſhe them therefore, whereof folowes that theſe olde whores ſometime ſel wenches bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cheape then fiſhers doe lamperyes. O beholde the company of the court, the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3663:47"/> holines, the religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the brotherhed, and finally the foule diſorder of the ſame. And I ſay for my parte, goe to the court who will and there abyde, and triumph who will: as for my ſelfe I do remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber I am a chriſten man, &amp; that I muſt accompt for the tyme I haue loſt, and therfore I had much rather to labor and dygge and delue out of the court and be ſaued, then to be nigh the kyng, my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience not cleane nor pure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>The xii. Chapiter. ¶ That in the court of princes all ſay wee will doe it, but none doe it.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Yas</hi> the great Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher of great renoume amonges the <hi>Grecians,</hi> ſayde vpon a tyme to the great <hi>Alexander Quilibet in ſuo nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, hebetior eſt qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in alieno,</hi> meaning, that commonly euerye man is more blinded in his owne affayres then in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
<pb facs="tcp:3663:48"/> mannes. And he ſo ſayd by ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good reaſon,<note place="margin">Moſt men are wiſeſt in other mens matters</note> for that there bee men, which for to geue a wiſe deliberate and ſage cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſail for to remedy a ſodain miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, haue excellent wittes, ſo that it be in another mannes matter. But in their owne affayres they haue neyther witte to gouerne their own houſes, nor ſtable minde to couer their owne miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>Cayus Iulius Caeſar, Octauus Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus, Marcus Antonius, Septimius Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerus, Marcus Aurelius,</hi> &amp; other in great nomber, that were eſtéemed in theyr priuy buſines,<note place="margin">Some can go nerue the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth which cannot gouerne their owne houſes.</note> that is to ſay, in the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng of the common wealth were won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders wittie: but we read that they wer ſo negligent in gouerning theyr owne houſholdes, their wiues &amp; their family, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it is much to their ſhame &amp; reproche: therfore ſuch be ſéene often to be good to rule y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> welth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be nothing worth to gouerne their owne, &amp; had need (if it might be honeſtly ſayd) to haue a ruler to rule the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Plutarch</hi> reporteth that the noble &amp; valia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t capitain <hi>Niſeas</hi> neuer loſt battail,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>lfe likyng h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>eth.</note> but onely in truſting to much to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3663:48"/> his own wit &amp; iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And if we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue <hi>Hiarcus</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Philoſopher, it is more hurtful to a man to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in his own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to pha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſy a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for in louing a woman, a man hurteth but himſelfe: but in ſticking to much to his own pha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſy, it may redou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hurt of a whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale. Al this y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is ſaid, ſhalbe to admoniſh them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tary in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> court, to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſant w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> the graue &amp; ſage perſons: and with ſuch as be learned, &amp; ſuch as haue good experience: For the graue, learnes vertue:<note place="margin">Scilence and experience.</note> Scilence is a certayne guide to a man: &amp; experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macion of all. For although y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courtier being yong, be neuer ſo ſage, graue, rich or in fauor,<note place="margin">The guides of a young cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier.</note> he ſhall néed a father to cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſail hym, a brother to perſuade hym a guide to teache him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way, &amp; a maiſter to inſtruct him, &amp; a corrector to punyſh him, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miſchifes, craftes, &amp; wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes doth ſo abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> court y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it is impoſſible y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alone may defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al, &amp; vtterly reſiſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> court there is none ſo high away to deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as for a man to be gouerned onely
<pb facs="tcp:3663:49"/> by himſelfe, and haue his owne ſwing.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A definition of the court.</note>The court is a perpetuall dreame, a botomeleſſe whorlepole, an inchaunted phantaſy, and a maſe: when he is in, he cannot get out till be bee mor founded. One of the beſt remedies that the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier may get againſt ſo many euils,<note place="margin">A faithfull frende is a great helpe to a Courtier.</note> is to haue a faythfull frende that flatters him nothing, but that rather will cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and rebuke him if he go home late, if he walk by night, if he be a falſe play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or whorehunter. But where ſhall we fynde ſuch a frende: For we ſee the frendſhip in the court is commonly v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed among young courtiers in this ſort, that ſo ſoone as two or thrée are met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,<note place="margin">Faithfull frendes are ſeldom found in the court.</note> ſtraite fall they to quarellyng, fighting, ryoting, ſo that there is rather occaſion geuen to do euil, then good cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſail to refraine. Therfore he that haun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the court, it were meete that he had ſome frende to whom without feare he might common of his buſines, and that the multitude be alſo to hym common frendes, but aboue all one perfit frend.</p>
               <p>I would alſo he ſhould keepe himſelf
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3663:49"/> from the conuerſacion of ſedicious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,<note place="margin">Sedicious perſons are to be auoyded.</note> from collericke perſons and vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bondes, for the raſcall ſorte will ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der &amp; ſay, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng payeth naught, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe which be in fauour haue all the ſwing, that the officers are proude, that mens ſeruice is euil recompenced, &amp; the good vnknowen: With theſe wordes and ſuch other lyke, the poore courtiers for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gettes to ſerue and begin to murmure.</p>
               <p>Alſo the good chriſtian man ought not to ceaſſe to amend his life,<note place="margin">Amendment or lyfe ſeldom practiſed in the court.</note> for that hée hopeth to liue long: although thoſe that be olde there occupy themſelues rather in new paſtance, then to correct theyr old ſinnes. Ye ſhal finde them that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe euery day for to amend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in their age, and yet neuertheles dye there worſe then deuils:<note place="margin">Amendment promiſed, but not performed</note> the cauſe is that they all ſay we wil doe and yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer do. There be ſome old doting fooles, which ſhal bragge of the kinges &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which they haue ſerued, of the chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of offices that they haue ſéene, and of the warres paſſed, and of the great mutabilitie &amp; chaunge of fortune. And
<pb facs="tcp:3663:50"/> yet notwithſtanding all that they haue ſéene and endured,<note place="margin">Doting cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers.</note> they be as gréedy of gayne, and delight in young and foolyſh paſtymes as though they were newe to begyn to lyue. Alas miſerable men that in perpetuall trauail, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſorow, &amp; infinite trouble haue paſſed theyr lyues, euen from their firſt time of knowledge (which is, xv. yeares) to the tyme of manhood, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from that tyme to their doting age, and all to haue gayned riches and increaſe in renoune: not in all this tyme once reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that in ſteade of a true and perfite reſt, they prepare for themſelues a hell both for bodye and ſoule. The courtier al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ought not lightly to complayne of aduerſities which many tymes come to hym, thinking that oftentymes (though it bee our owne faulte) wee doe complayne of thynges whyche ſhoulde complayne of vs, if they had a toungue.</p>
               <p>What time a man ſéeth him ſelf baſe and is litle eſtéemed, or poore and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of the rich, and deceiued of that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3663:50"/> he looked ſurely to haue,<note place="margin">Fortune is not the cauſe of pouertie.</note> incontinent he curſes his fortune and lamentes his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil: In the meane whyle it is not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune that hath thus ſerued him, but him ſelfe that hath ſerched it and founde it. Such a man thinkes to bee quickelye rich, honored and eſtéemed, that ſhortly after ſeeth himſelf poore, ouerthrowen, diſpiſed, and blamed of all men, &amp; can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reuenge himſelfe, but onely ſay, he is vnfortunate &amp; vnhappy to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, and that it is miſhap: which is not ſo, but his owne folly that makes hym to leaue the ſuretie of his houſe, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth himſelf to the hazard of fortune, and therfore hath no cauſe to complain but of himſelfe which chooſe the way to it. The beſt is, after that a man pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth himſelf to continue in the court,<note place="margin">Pacient diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblers come to preferment in the court.</note> that then paciently he awaite and fary the tyme of auauncement or auau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage that he looketh for: or els if he cannot paciently diſſemble with the tyme, let him not remayne there,<note place="margin">Contentacion wherein it con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiſteth.</note> for contentaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conſiſteth not in the place, but in the ambicious heart, and troubled mynde.
<pb facs="tcp:3663:51"/> And take this for a trueth, ye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers that if .ij. or .iij. thinges ſuccéed to your purpoſe proſperouſly, there ſhall come a hundreth ouerthwart the ſhins, either to you or to your frendes. For notwithſtanding that the courtiers do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges and deſires come to good paſſe, there ſhalbe thinges for his frend or fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that goeth all awrye, wherby often tymes he laments the hurt of his frend, and that which is denied him more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pleaſure he hath of his owne happe: wherefore there is alwayes lacke or faute of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentacion. Wil ye any more? the being in court or out of the court, ye ſhall beare no other matter,<note place="margin">Newes is all that is ſought for in the court.</note> then, what newes at the court? what doth the king? where is he? where is the counſail? and where lieth the officers of the houſhold? and this is moſt true, that they which deſire to heare ſuch newes, are as deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to ſée newes: And by this meanes the poore wene to make themſelues riche, the rich the more to commaund, and the lords the more to rule. O what a pleaſure is it for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> court
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:3663:51"/> hoping that the king may know them, that thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be in fauor may dye, or that fortune may chaunge, &amp; that they come forward? And it foloweth, that in tary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the tyme, the tyme deceiueth them, and then death taketh them vnware.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>The .xiij. Chapiter. ¶ That there is a ſmal nomber of them that be good in the court, and a great nomber of good in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Lutarch</hi> in the booke intitled <hi>De exilio</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth of the great King <hi>Ptolome,</hi> that hauing on a daye at ſupper with hym ſeuen Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours of diuers prouinces, moued a queſtion to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which of al their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealthes gouerned themſelues with beſt lawes &amp; cuſtomes? The ſayde Ambaſſadours, were <hi>Romayns, Carthagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niens, Ciciliens, Rhodiens, Atheniens, Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niens,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3663:52"/> &amp; <hi>Cicioniens:</hi> among whom the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion was effectually debated afore the kyng, foraſmuch as euery one of them beyng affectionate to his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey alea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the wiſeſt reaſon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he could. The good king deſirous to know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth and the reſolucion of the queſtion, commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that euery one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ambaſſadours ſhuld tell of the beſt lawes or cuſtomes that were in their common welth thrée poyntes, and that thereby it might ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilye bee ſéene which was better ruled and deſerued more praiſe. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Am<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>baſſadour of the <hi>Romaynes</hi> began &amp; ſayd, In <hi>Rome</hi> the temples be honored,<note place="margin">The gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Rome. The gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage.</note> the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours obeied &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euil chaſtiſed. The Ambaſſadour of <hi>Carthage</hi> ſaid, in <hi>Carthage</hi> the noble men neuer ceaſe to prepare to the warre, the poore people to trauail, and the Philoſophers to teach.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Cicill.</note>The Ambaſſadours of the <hi>Ciciliens</hi> ſayd, In <hi>Cicill</hi> is true iuſtice executed, trouth is beloued, and equalitie praiſed. The Ambaſſadour of the <hi>Rhodiens</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">The gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Rhodiens.</note> In <hi>Rhodes</hi> the olde men are honeſt, the young men ſhamefaſte, and the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3663:52"/> women méeke and gentle. The Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour of the <hi>Atheniens</hi> ſayd,<note place="margin">The gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Atheniens.</note> the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniens</hi> doe not conſent that the riche ſhould bee parciall, nor the meane peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple idle, nor the gouernours without learnyng. The Ambaſſadour of the <hi>Lacedemoniens</hi> ſayde,<note place="margin">The gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lacedemoni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ens.</note> in <hi>Lacedemony</hi> enuye raynes not becauſe all are equal, nor couetouſnes becauſe all is common, nor idlenes becauſe all men trauayl. The Ambaſſadour of <hi>Cicioniens</hi> ſayd,<note place="margin">The gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Cicioniens.</note> in <hi>Cicion</hi> they receiue no ſtraungers, inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of newes, nor Phiſicions that kyll the whole, nor aduocates that makes the proceſſes immortall.</p>
               <p>When kyng <hi>Ptolome</hi> and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany had heard theſe ſo good and holy obſeruaunces, he prayſed greatly the inſtitucion of euery of them, ſaying, that he could not iudge which was the beſt. This hiſtory is well woorthy to be noted, and better to be folowed: And I beleue if in our dayes ſo many Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours ſhould meete, diſputing as theſe did of their common wealthes, they ſhould finde mo thinges to blame
<pb facs="tcp:3663:53"/> and ſpeake euill of (and that without compariſon) then to praiſe &amp; commend. In tymes paſſed the kings houſes were ſo well reformed,<note place="margin">Vice was ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in olde tyme.</note> the kinges the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ſo wyſe, and the gouernours ſo mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, that litle offences were chaſtized, and once to think of great offences for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden: to the entent that the chaſtice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be terrour to the euil, and the prohibicion a plain aduice vnto the good: It is not ſo in our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welthes, where is done ſo much euil, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſo many bitter offences and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happines,<note place="margin">Sinne is leſſe accounted of in our dayes than in olde tyme.</note> that thoſe which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auncients did chaſtice for deadly ſinnes by death, wee diſſemble to bee but veniall: the truans and wantons be ſo entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as though we lacked them: and not as méete to be chaſed and driuen away. My Lady the widow, or my maiſtres that is maried, if they fall to leude and wanton liuyng, ye ſhall not finde one that wil ſay madam or maiſters ye doo naught:<note place="margin">Sinne is com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reproofe.</note> but rather ſixe hundreth that ſhall procure her diſhonor.</p>
               <p>This is in our time, ſuch is our faſhion
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3663:53"/> and maners which cauſeth euill: ſo that he is more to be praiſed which may be called good in our common wealth, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any of the Conſuls of <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe that in the olde tyme it was almoſt a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous thing to finde one euil among a hundreth, and now it is a great chaunce to finde one good amongſt a hundreth.</p>
               <p>The holy ſcripture prayſeth <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> that was iuſt in <hi>Calde, <hi>Loth</hi>
                  </hi> that was iuſt in <hi>Sodom, <hi>Daniel</hi>
                  </hi> in <hi>Babilon, <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi>
                  </hi> in <hi>Niniuie,</hi> and <hi>Neemyas</hi> in <hi>Damaſco.</hi> And lykewyſe may we among this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thalog of holy men nomber the good courtiers if there be any,<note place="margin">A good cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier is a blacke ſwanne.</note> but it cannot be foraſmuche as none goeth about to moue the courtiers to vertue, but that counſail them to perdicion.</p>
               <p>There is in the court ſo many vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bondes, ſo many players, blaſphemers, and deceiuers, that we may be abaſhed to ſée ſuch a multitude: but it were a noueltie to heare of the contrarye, for why? the world hath nothing in his ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiers but thornes, and for frutes of trées,<note place="margin">The world is repleniſhed with counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feite treaſure.</note> but leaues, for vines but bryers, and in
<pb facs="tcp:3663:54"/> their garnerdes but ſtrawe, and in their treaſures, but Alcumin. O golden worlde, O worlde deſired, O worlde paſſed: the difference betwixt you and vs is, that afore you litle and litle the worlde paſſeth, but afore vs it is quite paſſed. In thée O world euery man vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaketh to inuent, to doe, to begyn and to make an end of that he will: and that which is worſt of all, liueth as he will: but the ende is right doubtfull. There is litle to bée truſted in thée O worlde.<note place="margin">The world is not to be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted.</note> And contrariwyſe litle to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende, litle to enioy, and very little to kéepe. There are many thinges to bée deſired, many thinges to be amended, and many thinges to be lamented. Our aunceters had the Iron world, but our world may well bee called the dirtie world,<note place="margin">The world is repleniſhed with filthines.</note> becauſe it kepeth vs conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually in a filthy myer, and alwayes we be there in defiled and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:3663:54"/>
               <head>The .xiiij. Chapiter. ¶Of many affaires in the court, and that there be better huſbandmen, then commonly is of courtiers.</head>
               <p>THe Poet <hi>Homer</hi> hath written of the trauels of <hi>Vlixes</hi> one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the <hi>Greekes: <hi>Quintus Curtius</hi>
                  </hi> of <hi>Alexander</hi> &amp; <hi>Darius: Moyſes</hi> of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> And of them of <hi>Egipt: <hi>Samuel</hi>
                  </hi> of <hi>Dauid</hi> and of <hi>Saul: Titus Liuius,</hi> of the <hi>Romains: <hi>Thucidides</hi>
                  </hi> of <hi>Iaſon</hi> with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Minotaure: and <hi>Saluſt</hi> of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ugurth</hi> and <hi>Cathelyne.</hi> I the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> willing to folow theſe good auctors, haue vndertaken to wryte the vnkynd trauayles of the court that the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers of our tyme haue which haue pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience enough for to ſuffer them, and no wyſedome to auoyde them: then it is not wythout a cauſe if I doe call the trauayles of the courte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde,<note place="margin">Vnkinde tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueils of the court.</note> for they bée accuſtomed vnto it as the olde horſes are to the packeſadle
<pb facs="tcp:3663:55"/> and to the plough, ſith that the courtiers themſelues do ſuffer them ſo much and haue no profite thereof. Some men wil ſay that I am euill aduiſed becauſe I write y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courtiers haue not their eaſe, ſeeing that he that may attaine to be in the court is accompted to be fortunate. But he abuſeth him ſelfe, if he thynke that all ſuch as are out of the court bée beaſtes and ignorant perſons, and hée only wyſe: they rude and he delicate: he honored and they vile, they ſtamme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and he eloquent.</p>
               <p>If it were ſo that God would that the moſt perfite men ſhould be in the court, it ſhould be to vs more then a fault, not incontinently to be a courtier: know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ther can be no better time em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, then that which is beſtowed in hearing the wyſe and ſage men: but when all is ſayd, the places doe not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the men,<note place="margin">The place bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth not the man, but the man the place.</note> but the men the places. God knowes (for example) how many gentle and good honeſt myndes labor in the villages, and how many fooles and lubbers brag it in palaices. God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:3663:55" rendition="simple:additions"/> how many wel ordered wittes and iudgementes is hid in the villages,<note place="margin">Fooles in the court haue countenance when as wiſe men in villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ar obſcure</note> and how many rude wits &amp; weake braines face and brace in the court. How many be ther in the court the which although they haue offices, dignities, eſtates, and préeminences, yet in the village (after a maner of ſpeakyng) with great payne they are not able to rule .x. men. How many come out of the court correcters of other, that themſelues in the villages ſhuld be corrected? O how many things is ſayd amonges y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore laborers wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be noted? And contrary, ſpoken afore princes worthy to be mocked? O howe many is in the court that make themſelues highly to be eſtéemed, not for to be honeſt &amp; diligent, but to come in auctoritie? And how many is there in the village forgotten and not ſet by, more for lacke of fauor then for either lacke of witte or diligence: The prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces geue the offices: Thoſe that be in fauor haue the entry: nature, the good bloud: The parentes, the patrimony: and the deſeruing, honor: but to wyſe
<pb facs="tcp:3663:56"/> and ſage commeth onely of God,<note place="margin">Wiſedom and vertue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of God.</note> &amp; men haue not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power to take it away. And if it were ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> princes might geue good witte to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they would, they ſhoulde kéepe it for themſelues,<note place="margin">Princes neuer looſe, but for lack of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</note> ſeyng they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer léeſe, but for lacke of knowlege. I take it for an euil point of ſuch as new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come from the court to the village, &amp; being there, rather vſe mockyng then taſt the benefite thereof. But in the meane tyme, thou ſéeſt their maner of life, that is, to go to bed at midnight and riſe at .x. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clocke, &amp; in making readye till noone,<note place="margin">A Courtiers lyfe.</note> trimmyng their buſhe, or beard, and ſettyng the cap awry. And all the day after, to talke of his darling that he hath in the court, or of the battel of <hi>Granado</hi> wher he did meruails.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ragginge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ourtiers.</note> And ſome there be of them that will lye and bragge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were at the iorney of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uay</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the capitaine <hi>Antony Deleua:</hi> at <hi>Tunes</hi> with the Emperour: or at <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> with <hi>Andrew Doria.</hi> And for all his brabling he was no better then a ruffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an or a zacar of <hi>Tholydo,</hi> or a knaue of <hi>Cordoua.</hi> We haue reherſed theſe things
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3663:56"/> before writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to cauſe our minion friſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers to leaue mocking of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitantes of the village, eſtéeming the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be but fooles and lurdens. For I beleue, if my maiſter the Emperor would ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh all the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of fooles,<note place="margin">If fooles were baniſhed the court the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour ſhoulde be left alone.</note> I feare me he were lyke to dwell alone in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> court. Let vs ſay the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that very late they of the court know the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> order of their life &amp; profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Courtly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</note> I mean y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which thei kepe ſtraitly, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſtes in this: they promiſe to pleaſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuil, &amp; to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> court, &amp; to folow the world: They promiſe to be euer pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſife, ſad &amp; ful of ſuſpicion: They promiſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to be chopping &amp; chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging, ful of buſines, to bye, to ſell, to wéepe, to ſin, &amp; neuer to reforme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues: They pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe alſo to be iagged &amp; ragged, an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gred, indebted &amp; diſpiſed: they promyſe to ſuffer rebukes of lords, theft of their neighbors, iniuries of colerike me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, moc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keries of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, reproch of their pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes: &amp; finally, miſſing &amp; lacking of fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds.</p>
               <p>Lo this is the profeſſion and rule of the obſeruauntes of the court: which
<pb facs="tcp:3663:57" rendition="simple:additions"/> I will not name a rule,<note place="margin">Confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and diſorder of the court.</note> but a confuſion: not a order but a diſorder, not a mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, but a hell, and a religion not of brethren, but of diſſolute perſons: no poore Hermites but couetous worldely men. O pittie, O lacke of good iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Oracle of <hi>Apollo</hi> beyng aſked by the Ambaſſadours of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines</hi> wher lay the poynt for one to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne himſelfe wel,<note place="margin">A rule for a man to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne himſelfe by.</note> The anſwer was, for a man to know wel his own eſtate and degrée, that thereby one may rule his deſires, and bridle his affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. The courtier deſiring all, and perſeueryng in nothing, ſhall thinke in his mynde, that if he get not in one yeare ſome fée or office, that it is not for lack of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege: but as a perſon ignorant and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe blameth his fortune, and curſeth the houre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer he came thether, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out callyng to mynde that the court is as the Palme trée whoſe roote is a fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome vnder the ground, before that he ſhewe two fingers brede of leaues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the ground.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>loweth long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e.</note> In like maner, a man muſt be long in ſeruice before he be pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moted:
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:3663:57"/> yet ſo much reſteth that the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuering and abidyng by it, cauſeth a man to hope: For to ſay the truth, it is ſéene, if there bée thrée which deſerue more then they haue, there be thrée hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth that haue more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they deſerue. O how ſeldome tymes doeth fortune that ſhe ought for to doe?<note place="margin">Fortune ſell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom doeth geue to men that which they deſerue.</note> And how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tymes fortunes hazard and chaunce doeth better then the aſſurance of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue? becauſe ſhe meaſures her merites by the euil length of opinion, and not by reaſon: ſhe makes the water burne without fyre, the knife to cutte without ſtéele, the Candle to light w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out flame, the Mill to goe without water,<note place="margin">Fortune is vnconſtant.</note> and the cauſe is only her inconſtancy. If ſhee laugh in the court of any, it is but with her eares, If ſhée wéepe, it had béen bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter neuer for a man to come out of hys houſe: If ſhée lifte any vp aloft, it is to throwe him downe agayne lower then he was: If ſometyme ſhée diſſemble, it is to take one in a trap. Let no man the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> truſt of fortune, for ſhée is ſo varyable, that ſhée neuer holdeth her promyſe of
<pb facs="tcp:3663:58" rendition="simple:additions"/> that ſhée geueth, neyther by worde nor yet by writing that ſhée maketh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>The xv. Chapiter. ¶That among courtiers is neither kept amitie nor faithfulnes: And how much the Court is full of trauail, of enuy and rancour.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt exceſſiue trauailes amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers is, that none is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident there w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out he be hated or at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he hate: that is not purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or els doeth purſue, that doeth not mocke or els is mocked.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Courtly diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation.</note>And one vnhappy thing is in the court, many there be that will doe of theyr bonette to you, that gladly woulde ſée your heades of by the ſhoulders: And ſuch there be that makes reuerence vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you that would haue his legge bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to ſée you dead and caried to your graue: Is it not a great pitie to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaunt all day together, to laugh and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:3663:58"/> make mery one with another,<note place="margin">Hatred, vnder the coullour of frendſhip.</note> and yet haue mortall hate? Is not this more then a diſſimulacion, to honor hym whom they would be glad to ſée led to the gallous? One thyng for all, it is ambicion &amp; to much hope of ſharpe and bitter fortune, and lacke of knowledge, of this, that amitie well obſerued, is much worth to moderate a man.</p>
               <p>What lyfe, what fortune, what taſte may he take that ſéeth himſelfe dayly preſent in the court, where is ſo muche theft, bribry, murders, poyſoners, felo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and traytours ready to betray and ſell a man, &amp; be himſelf betrayed and ſolde? And contrariwiſe what felicitie is it to be in the company of thoſe, with whom a man may faythfully recreate himſelf fearyng no man? In the court, there be gentlemen ſo rooted in vengeaunce and hatred that by no meane, requeſt, nor gentlenes a man may direct them from their euil ententes, in ſuch maner that they be glad to make warre with their owne houſes, to chace peace from them ſelues to the houſes of their enemies?
<pb facs="tcp:3663:59" rendition="simple:additions"/> Whereby one may well preſuppoſe as is aforeſayd, that vnneth one may hope to haue frendes in the court, and leſſe truſt: &amp; the greater men are in auctori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the more afrayde they bee to fall. What then cauſes a man there to tary in ſuch trauail? I haue wonder that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny can ſuffer it or haue a heart to diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it.<note place="margin">The countrey man is happy and the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier miſerable.</note> O how fortunate is he that lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his lyfe in the village, with the meane buſines of his litle poſſeſſion, in compariſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the courtier whoſe eſtate is euer vnhappy and of all partes miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, that neuer ceaſes to hope of thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges vayne, in procuring vniuſt thinges and ſuch thinges that neuer can be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined. And if thoughts were wynd, and his deſires waters, it ſhuld be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter daunger to ſaile in his heart then in the maine ſea. In the court is one thing I wotte not what,<note place="margin">Three things in the court.</note> &amp; one thing I knowe not howe, and one thing I vnderſtande not, which cauſeth there inceſſauntlye complaintes, and continuall choppyng and chaunging, and euermore diſpyte and enuy: and that worſt is, there is no
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3663:59"/> libertie to depart thence.</p>
               <p>The yoke of the court is hard, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bondes faſt tyed,<note place="margin">Courtiers are tyed to the court.</note> and the plough ſo tedious that thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wene to be the firſt to triumph, are the firſt that labor and drawe the weightie burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. And ſuch as are poore and ignoraunt men ſuffer theſe intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable trauailes, becauſe they would not be as ſubiectes in their own countreis, and to haue a greater libertie to doe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil. But God knowes what ſuch liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie coſteth them,<note place="margin">The libertie of the court, brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth perpetual bondage.</note> that for a ſhorte and vaine pleaſure purchaſe to themſelues, continuall trauail and perpetuall bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage. The propertie of this vicious li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, or better to call it, this miſchée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſubiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, that at the beginning it ſéemeth ſomewhat pleaſaunt: but in the ende all conuertes to a bitternes, ſorow, and lamentacion, chiefly when a man hath experience by litle and litle of the vice that this life conteineth. For if he accompany with women, he muſt flatter them, ſerue them, and intreate them: And if money lacke,<note place="margin">Shiftes are made for lack of money.</note> then muſt there be ſome deuiliſh ſhift made.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3663:60"/>
               <p>For why, when one commeth new to the court, my lady dame gorgious, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des him a trayne, ſhée entertaines him, ſhée makes much on him, ſhée colles him: but when ſhée ſpieth him to lacke, ſhée ſendes him to paſture in the bare fieldes.<note place="margin">Money cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> And if the tyme of eating come, the courtier muſt often times féed with them, whom he would ſée eaten with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſauce: Now, if his turne be to play, therin is litle profite: if he win, he muſt liberally depart with the gaine to thoſe that ſtand by: and if he looſe, they reſtore to him neuer a penny. And if the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers turne be to ieſt, and to bee mery, therein he findeth no fruit, for the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers playe beginneth in fayre wordes, and endes with braulyng, chidyng, and fighting. And foraſmuche as it is the worſt life of all other lyues: Let vs conclude that there is nothyng worſe then a vayne cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier,<note place="margin">A vaine cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier &amp; an idle huſbandman are the worſt men.</note> and an idle huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:3663:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>The .xvi. Chapiter. ¶By how much the common wealthes and the courtes of the tyme paſſed were more perfite then the courtes of the tyme preſent.</head>
               <p>THe king <hi>Anchiſes</hi> did lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the proude <hi>Troye,</hi> done by the princes of <hi>Greece:</hi> The Quéene <hi>Roſaine</hi> bewailed her huſband <hi>Darius,</hi> when he was ouercome by the great <hi>Alexander.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ieremy</hi> the Prophet complained the eſtate of <hi>Babilon,</hi> when it was held cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue. Kyng <hi>Dauid</hi> lamented his ſonne <hi>Abſolon</hi> when <hi>Ioab</hi> kylde hym. The Lady <hi>Cleopatra</hi> thought no nother but to dye for ſorow when her deare &amp; wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued <hi>Marcus Antonius</hi> was van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed by the Emperour <hi>Auguſtus.</hi> The Conſul <hi>Marcus Marcellus</hi> lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Citie of <hi>Syracuſe</hi> when he ſawe it on fyre. <hi>Saluſt, Rome,</hi> euil gouerned.</p>
               <p>The Patriarche <hi>Iacob</hi> hys ſonne
<pb facs="tcp:3663:61"/> 
                  <hi>Ioſeph:</hi> The king <hi>Demetrius</hi> his good father <hi>Antigonus,</hi> when he found him dead at the battail of <hi>Marathone.</hi> It ſhalbe alſo conuenient that amonges theſe well renoumed princes we ſhould lament the miſeries of our tyme, in the which we ſée thinges ſo merueylous, that the curious auctours of the tyme paſſed, neuer wrote thinges ſemblable vnto them: Nor the men in thoſe dayes neuer ſawe the lyke. Truth it is that the Chroniclers in thoſe dayes wrote what they would, In our tyme ſcant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man dare ſpeake.</p>
               <p>The Philoſopher <hi>Ariminius</hi> hath written of the aboundaunce of <hi>Egipt: <hi>Demophon</hi>
                  </hi> of the fartilitie of <hi>Arabia: <hi>Thucidides</hi>
                  </hi> of the treaſures of <hi>Tyrus: <hi>Aſclepius</hi>
                  </hi> of the Mynes of <hi>Europe: <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drillus</hi>
                  </hi> in the commendacion and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinges of <hi>Grece: <hi>Leonides</hi>
                  </hi> of the trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phes of <hi>Thebes: <hi>Eumenides</hi>
                  </hi> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Athens: <hi>Theſiphontes</hi>
                  </hi> of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that is kepte in the court, and of the princely houſes of the <hi>Siciomens: <hi>Pitheas</hi>
                  </hi> of the profit that came by the litle ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:3663:61" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the diſciples of <hi>Socrates: Apolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> of the continencie &amp; abſtinence that was kepte in ſchooles of the diuine <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: Myronides</hi> of the great exerciſe, and of the litle reſt that was in the houſe of <hi>Hyarcus: Aulus Gelyus</hi> of the tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and litle eating, and of the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſléeping of the diſciples of maiſter <hi>Fauorimus: Plutarch</hi> of the wyſe wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>Greece,</hi> and of the chaſte wyues of <hi>Rome: <hi>Dyodorus,</hi>
                  </hi> how thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> were inhabitants in the Iſles of <hi>Balyares</hi> caſt their treaſure into the ſea for feare leſt the ſtraungers for couetouſnes of their riches ſhould make them warres, and to the entente alſo that no parcialitie ſhould grow among themſelues.</p>
               <p>Hearyng then all this that I haue ſayd, I demaund of the reader hys ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyſe what my penne ſhould wryte of our tyme? If we ſhould write of boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and veritie, we ſhould falſely lye: If of riches, men be ſo gréedy that all be diſpoſed to deſyre and hunger couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.<note place="margin">Couetouſnes in all men.</note> How ſhall we then prayſe the men of our tyme? Shall wée ſay they bee
<pb facs="tcp:3663:62" rendition="simple:additions"/> hardy and puiſſaunt and learned, and we ſée that they employ their myndes to nothing els but to robbe and beguile eche one the other?<note place="margin">Robbery.</note> How ſhall we praiſe them of prſoperitie and health, ſeeyng that the peſtilence &amp; the French pockes more then common is among them?<note place="margin">French pocks a common diſeaſe.</note> How ſhall wee commende their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinencie and abſtinence, ſéeyng that ſcant in fiftie yeares ye ſhall not finde one that will bridle his luſt and deſire?<note place="margin">Vnbrideled affections.</note> Shall we praiſe them of litle reſt and of much exerciſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſée that there is a greater nomber that geue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to idlenes and thefery,<note place="margin">Idlenes.</note> then to honeſt trauails &amp; paynes? How ſhal we praiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of temperate eating,<note place="margin">Surfeyting.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſée in our dayes the belly is mens God? How ſhall we commende them for hauyng chaſt women and obedient, ſeyng that there is nothing more common amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them then adultery?<note place="margin">Adultery.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Shall we ſay, they be not couetous, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng that not onely men ſerch golde and ſiluer in déepe mynes, but men trauail to ſéeke it as farre as the Indiens, of a
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:3663:62"/> vyneyarde ſo froſen, of a trée ſo dry, of fruit ſo vnrype, of a water ſo troubled, of bread ſo euil baken, of ſo much falſe golde, of a worlde ſo ſuſpicious, what ſhall we hope any other therof but euil and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion? Let vs reade that is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of the courtes of the princes of <hi>Siria,</hi> of <hi>Percia,</hi> of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> of <hi>Crecia,</hi> and final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the <hi>Romaines:</hi> And let vs conferre theſe to our courtes, and ye ſhal ſée ſuch euils and vicious cuſtomes in our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealthes, that the auncientes did neuer attaine to the knowlege how to commit ſuche abhominacions, nor yet (I ſay) to inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſuch euils. In thoſe moſt happy tymes and golden worldes an euil condicioned man ſcant durſt to haue ſhewed himſelfe in anye honeſt company: but now alas (a thing to be lamented) the worlde is ſo repleniſhed with diſſolute and corrupt liuing, that it is counted but a ſmall faulte to bée euil, except he be ſuch a one as is paſt al ſhame &amp; grace. The cortiers wil not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny me but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiles they geue atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vpriſing of their maiſters, they
<pb facs="tcp:3663:63"/> tell eche one the other what paſtyme they haue had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night before,<note place="margin">Vain delights of the court.</note> how they haue played, ſworne and ſtared at their game, of their laughinges, &amp; the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies they haue had w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle dames: which of them was fayreſt &amp; beſt appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relled? &amp; ſometime in ſecret of thoſe that they haue committed adultery withal.</p>
               <p>And thus, as the worlde is new, the inuencions are new, the playes newe, the garments new, new ſpeaking, new maners,<note place="margin">New fangled thinges.</note> and euery yeare, euery moneth yea and euery day, and euery houre: we ſee vices ſo largely delated, &amp; vertue ſo diminiſhed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am aſhamed to write it: And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true cauſe is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> court ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue hath many controllers &amp; enemyes,<note place="margin">Vertue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolled: &amp; vice vpholden.</note> and vice innumerable vpholders and maynteiners. For if there be brought into the court one laudable cuſtome, it is no ſooner come, but forthwith it is chaſed away: And on the other parte, vice cannot ſo ſoone appeare, but it is as ſoone embraſed and entertained. The ſage lawyer <hi>Lygurgus</hi> did defende ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely by a lawe that the ſtraungers
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3663:63"/> ſhould not know the ſecrets of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welth nor that his citezens ſhould meddle much abroad, for that purpoſe as is ſayd, that in medling with them, they ſhould not learne their vices nor their barberous condicions.</p>
               <p>In the tyme when <hi>Marcus Portius</hi> was Conſull,<note place="margin">An example of a Muſitian.</note> there came an excellent Muſicia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of <hi>Grece</hi> into <hi>Rome,</hi> which for becauſe that he put one ſtring more on his harpe then was accuſtomed to bée played withall, he was by the conſent of the people baniſhed from <hi>Rome</hi> &amp; hys harp burnt: Howbeit in this our time, we could wel agrée w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Muſique, &amp; wold not paſſe how many ſtrings y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> harp had: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might agrée &amp; ſtay themſelues.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſayeth that he ſawe once at <hi>Rome</hi> a prieſt of <hi>Greece</hi> ſtoned to death in the great place of <hi>Campus Marcus,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that he did ſacrifice to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goddeſſe <hi>Berecinthe</hi> in other maner then they were accuſtomed to be ſacrificed vnto. <hi>Suetonius</hi> that affirmeth that in .iiij.C.lxiiij. yeares which was the tyme that the temple <hi>Vierges Vaſtales</hi> endured,
<pb facs="tcp:3663:64"/> there was neuer founde but iiij. euill liuing perſons, which were <hi>Domicia, Rhea, Albina</hi> and <hi>Cornelia,</hi> the which for their offences were openly buryed quycke. If at this day one would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter the names of ſuch like, to be ſo pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhed, I leaue it to your iudgement whether there ſhould lacke ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gmen to doe execuſion. <hi>Threbelius Publius</hi> ſayd that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour <hi>Aurilianus Quintus</hi> toke a great frend of his fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> office of Dictator, which was named <hi>Rogerius,</hi> onely becauſe he had daunſed at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of <hi>Poſteria Auia</hi> his nigh neighbor ſaying,<note place="margin">Daunſing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the good Iudge ſhuld not leaue his grauitie &amp; vſe ſuch wylde and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon playes. But ſo it is, whatſoeuer this Emperour ſayde, In our tyme we will geue licence to iudges to remoue their féete as faſt as they will,<note place="margin">Bribery finely reproued.</note> ſo that they holde their handes ſtill. It ſhall make no matter to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore pleader whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his iudge ſing or daunce, ſo that he miniſter iuſtice with expedicion,<note place="margin">Expedition of cauſes in lawe.</note> that the poore man come not oftentimes and geue to muche attendance. In thys
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:3663:64"/> caſe it were very good to rayſe the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Domitian,</hi> which as <hi>Suetonius</hi> writeth made a lawe, that whoſoeuer prolonged the proces of his clyant more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one yeare, that he ſhould for euer be baniſhed <hi>Rome.</hi> If thys holy lawe had dured to this day, there ſhuld haue béen more baniſhed in <hi>Rome</hi> and els where, then there are now citizens.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>The .xvij. Chapiter. ¶Of diuers noble and valiaunt men, that left the court and the great cities and drew them to their proper houſes, more by will, then by neceſſitie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MArcus Craſſus</hi> a captaine of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines</hi> was greatly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended and praiſed for that he was valiaunt in the warre, and wiſe in the buſines of hys houſhold: This is that <hi>Craſſus</hi> that fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the parcialitie of the Conſul <hi>Silla</hi> againſt <hi>Marius</hi> and <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> after Dictator. It chaunſed on a tyme that
<pb facs="tcp:3663:65"/> by the fortune of the ſea, the ſayd <hi>Caeſar</hi> was priſoner to certaine Pyrates and robbers of the ſea, and he ſayd boldly to two or three of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt of them that kept him faſt bound, It doeth (ſayd he) gréeue me much, not for that I am taken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, foraſmuch as that is but hazarde of the warre, but of the pleaſure that myne enemye <hi>Craſſus</hi> will take when he doth heare of the newes.<note place="margin">The court is vtterly renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of Craſſus</note> This <hi>Craſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> was Maiſter to a Philoſopher na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Alexandrius,</hi> that gouerned hym as a father, counſailed him as a frende, and taught him as a maiſter: And this did he by the ſpace of .xviij. yeres, which paſſed, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he demaunded licence to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to his countrey: And going hys way, ſayd theſe words vnto <hi>Alexander:</hi> I aſke of thee none other rewarde for my pain, nor for my labors in teaching of thée, then to graunt that I ſhal neuer returne to the court agayne: and when I am gone that thou wilt neuer wryte vnto me of thine affaires, for that I am ſo wery of beyng a courtier, that I will not onely leaue the court, but alſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3663:65"/> all that euer I ſawe or heard in it. <hi>Denis</hi> of <hi>Siracuſe,</hi> albeit that hée was a cruel tyrant, yet notwithſtanding hée was a great frend to the Philoſophers, and a honorer of wyſe men. And he ſaid that he tooke much pleaſure to heare of the wyſe and ſage men of <hi>Greece,</hi> but hée beleued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not, becauſe their teachings were wordes without déedes.</p>
               <p>Seuen of the moſt ſageſt and beſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of <hi>Greece</hi> came to <hi>Siracuſe</hi> a Citie where the ſayde <hi>Denys</hi> was reſident: that is to ſay, <hi>Plato, Chylo, Demopho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Diogenes, Myrtho, Pyllades</hi> and <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranus,</hi> the which medled more of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of <hi>Denis</hi> then he did of their doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine. <hi>Diogenes</hi> dwelled a xi. yere with him, and after returned to his countrey, where he beyng and waſhing of herbes for hys dinner, another Philoſopher ſayd to him: If thou haddeſt not lefte the ſeruice of <hi>Denys</hi> thou néedeſt not now to haue taken the payne to waſhe thine owne herbes and make them rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for thy dinner. To whom <hi>Dyogines</hi> anſwered: If thou couldeſt haue beene
<pb facs="tcp:3663:66"/> content to haue waſhed &amp; eaten herbs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> needes not at this time to haue béen in the court of <hi>Dioniſius, Cato</hi> the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of whom the names of <hi>Cato</hi> firſte began, was eſtemed for one of the wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt of the Romaynes: And he was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſéene in .lxviii. yeres (for ſo long he liued) not once to laugh nor to do anye thing repugnant to his ſage grauitye. <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſayeth that he was in ſpeking prudent, gentle in conuerſacion, in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting ſharpe and ſeuere, in preſentes liberall: in eating ſober, and in that that he promiſed, ſure and certayn, and in executing iuſtice irreprehenſible.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Cato forſoke the court to dwell in a village.</note>After the age of .lv. yeres hée lefte the court of Rome, and withdrewe himſelf to a litle village nigh to <hi>Picene,</hi> which is now at this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ccalled <hi>Puzol:</hi> &amp; ther he paſſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſidue of his years in quiet and reſt, accompanied onely with his bookes, and taking for a ſinguler recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acion for to go twiſe or thriſe a day to walke in the fayr feilds and the vines, and him ſelfe oft to labor in them. And it fortuned on a day whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was abſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3663:66"/> from his houſe that one wrote with a cole vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his dore <hi>O felix Cato, tu ſolus ſcis viuere,</hi> which is to ſay, O happy <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> thou only knoweſt how to liue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lucullus</hi> Conſull and capitayn, a Romayn, right valiaunt brought to an end the warre agaynſt the Parthes which had continued by the ſpace of <hi>.16.</hi> yeres, whereby he gat great honour of the citezens of Rome, and immortall renoune for him ſelfe and great riches for his family. And it is ſayd of him that he only of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romaines did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioye peaceablye in his age, the ryches that he had wonne in his youth in the warres. And after when he came from <hi>Aſia</hi> and ſawe that the common welth was in deuiſion betwixte <hi>Marius</hi> and <hi>Silla,</hi> he determined to leaue Rome &amp; make a houſe in the countrey nighe to <hi>Naples</hi> vpon the Sea ſide (now at this preſent time called the Caſtle of Lobo) which he edified and liued there .xviii. yeres in great tranquilitie. His houſe was haunted with many people, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally with greate Capitaynes that
<pb facs="tcp:3663:67" rendition="simple:additions"/> we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t into <hi>Aſia,</hi> and with Ambaſſadours that came from <hi>Rome,</hi> which hée recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued very gently &amp; benignly. One night when his ſeruauntes had made readye his ſupper with a leſſe dyet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was accuſtomed to haue, they excuſing them ſelues that they ordayned the leſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had no ſtraungers: He ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, although ſayd hée, that there be no ſtraungers with me, know not you that <hi>Lucullus</hi> muſt ſuppe with <hi>Lucul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſpeaking of this valiaunt mans exerciſe that he did after he was retired to the place aforeſayd, ſayth that he delited much in hunting &amp; hawking, but aboue all pleaſures he moſt delited in his Library,<note place="margin">Reading of good thinges is a vertuous exerciſe.</note> there readyng and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting inceſſantly. <hi>Helius Spertianus</hi> ſayth that <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> after that hée had gouerned the Empyre xviij. yeares, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke it, and went to take his pleaſure in the fieldes, there in quiet to ende the reſidue of his lyfe, ſaying: that it was tyme for him to leaue the daungerous eſtates of the court and get hym to a
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:3663:67"/> peaceable life in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> village. Two yeres after he was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce retyred, the <hi>Romaines</hi> ſent vnto him a ſolemne Ambaſſade to inuite and deſire him effectuouſly that he would take pitie of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> welth, and return, promiſing him that ſo long as they liued there ſhould none haue the name of Emperour but hée. Now whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Ambaſſadours ariued at hys houſe, they found him in a litle garden where he was ſetting of Lettys and Onions: And hearing what they ſayd vnto him, he anſwered in this wyſe: Doe you not thinke my frendes, that it is much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for him that can ſowe his Lettys, and afterwarde pleaſantly and merely to eate the ſame, ſo ſtill to exerciſe him ſelfe, then to returne and enter into the goulfe of troubles in a common welth? I haue aſſayed both, I know what it is to commaund in the court, and what it is to liue &amp; labor in the village, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I pray you ſuffer me here to abide in pacience, for I deſire rather here to liue with the labor of my handes, then in the ſorow and cares of an Empyre.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3663:68"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The laborers lyfe is more to be deſired then the lyfe of a prince</note>Note by this example that the life of the laborer is more to be deſired then the life of a prince.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cleo</hi> and <hi>Pericles</hi> ſucceded in the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the common welth after <hi>Solon,</hi> a man excelently lerned and wel eſtée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and taken among the Grecians for halfe a God, by the reaſon of the wyſe lawes he made among the Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niens: Theſe two noble gouernoures were much beloued, becauſe that (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> telleth) <hi>Pericles</hi> which xxx. ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res had the adminiſtracion of the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and affaires of the cittie, was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſene to come into any mans houſe but his own, nor yet to ſit in anye open place among the common people, ſuche a grauity was in him.</p>
               <p>About the yeres of his age which was lx. he went from Athens to a litle vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage where hee ended the reſte of his dayes, ſtudying and paſſing the time in huſbandry, he had a litle ſmal gate or wicket in the entring of his houſe, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer which was written <hi>Inueni portu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſpes &amp; fortuna valete,</hi> That is to ſaye,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:3663:68"/> foraſmuch as now (and before I haue knowledge of vanity) I haue found the port of reſt, fye of hope, and fortune fare well. By this example, no courtier can ſay that he leadeth a ſure life, but onlye that courtier which doth as this wyſe captayn did withdraw him ſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lucius Seneca,</hi> was as who ſhould ſaye a right leder to good maners, and a in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructer to good letters to <hi>Nero</hi> the ſixt Emperour of Rome, with whom he ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ried. xxiiii yeres, and had great doings of thinges pertayning to the common wealth as wel of priuate cauſes as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, becauſe hee was ſage and of great experience. And at the laſt, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to greate age and weryed with the continuall conflictes and buſines of the court left the court and went and dwelt in a litle manſion he had nigh to <hi>Nolè Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pana,</hi> where hee liued after a longe time as witneſſeth his bokes <hi>De offiicis, de Ira, de bono viro, de aduerſa fortuna</hi> and other bokes which were to long to reherſe. At laſt (fortune &amp; mans malice did their office) <hi>Nero</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3663:69"/> commaunded him to be ſlayne, not for that he had committed any cryme wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to dye, or done any thing otherwiſe then an honeſt man ought to doe: but onely becauſe the lecherous <hi>Domicia</hi> hated him: Note well reader thys ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, that ſometime fortune purſueth him that forſaketh the court, aſwell as the courtier.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scipio</hi> the <hi>Affrican</hi> was ſo eſtéemed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Romaines,</hi> that in .xxii. yeares, whiles that he was in the warres hée neuer loſt battail: And yet made hée warre in <hi>Aſia, Europ,</hi> and <hi>Affrica,</hi> and to this, neuer committed acte worthy of reproch: And yet he wan <hi>Affrica</hi> &amp; put to ſacke <hi>Carthage,</hi> brought in bondage <hi>Numance,</hi> ouercame <hi>Hanniball,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored <hi>Rome</hi> weakened and nere deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the loſſe they had at the battail of <hi>Cannes.</hi> And yet for all this, beyng of the yeres of .lii. he withdrew him from the courte of <hi>Rome</hi> to a litle village be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Puzoll</hi> and <hi>Capua,</hi> where he liued a ſolitary life, and ſo conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t withal, that whiles he taried there a xi. yeres ſpace,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:3663:69"/> he neuer entred into <hi>Rome</hi> nor <hi>Capua.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The diuine <hi>Plato</hi> was borne in <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conia,</hi> and was noriſhed in <hi>Egipt,</hi> &amp; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in <hi>Athens:</hi> It is read of him, that he anſwered the Ambaſſadours of <hi>Cirene</hi> that required of him lawes to gouerne themſelues in ſure peace, in this wiſe: <hi>Difficilimum eſt homines ampliſſima fortuna ditatos legibus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinere.</hi> Which is to vnderſtand, that it is hard to bring to paſſe to make rich men to be ſubiect to the rigour of the lawe. To conclude, <hi>Plato</hi> not willing to abyde longer the clamor and cry of the court, went and dwelt in a litle village two miles from <hi>Athens</hi> called <hi>Academia,</hi> where the good old man after he had taryed there .xiiij. yeres, teaching and writing many no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table doctrines, ended there his moſte happy dayes. After the memory of him, the auncients called the village <hi>Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> which is to ſay in Engliſh, a ſchole: The concluſion is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all theſe honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſage princes &amp; wiſe men, left <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies,</hi> kingdomes, Cities, and great riches, and went into the vyllages,
<pb facs="tcp:3663:70"/> there to ſerche a poore, an honeſt, and a peaceable lyfe.</p>
               <p>Not that I will ſay that ſome of theſe lefte the court, to be there poore and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and rebuked, but of their frée wil and frée libertie, minding to liue a qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et and honeſt life or they dyed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>The xviij. Chapiter. ¶The aucthor complayneth with great reaſon, of the yeares that he loſt in the court.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Will demaunde of mine owne ſelf, mine owne life, and make accoumpt of the ſame, to the entent that I wil co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre my yeares to my trauailes, and my trauailes to my yeares, that it may appeare how long I left of to liue, and beganne to dye.</p>
               <p>My life (gentle reader) hath not béen a life, but a long death: my dayes a play new for to begyn: my yeares a verye tedious dreame:<note place="margin">The authors lyfe paſt.</note> my pleaſures Scorpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: my youth a tranſitorie fantaſye.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:3663:70"/> My proſperitie hath béen no proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritye: but properly to ſpeake, a pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Caſtell, and a treaſure of Alcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myn.</p>
               <p>I came to the court very yong, where I ſawe diuers maners of offices and chaunges, euen among the princes that I ſerued. And I haue aſſayed to trauail by ſea and by land, and my recompence was much more then I deſerued: and that was this, that ſometyme I was in fauor, and ſometyme out of fauor. I haue had experience of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſomer ſantes of deſtines: I haue had in the courte frendes and enemyes: I haue had falſe reports:<note place="margin">Inconſtant fortune.</note> I haue béen euen now glad and mery, and forthwith ſadde and ſory: to day rich, to morowe poore: now moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpwarde, &amp; ſtraite throwen doune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde: This hath been to me a maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, where I haue loſt boeth money and tyme. And now I ſay to thee my ſoule, what haſt thou gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this great iorney? The recompence is this,<note place="margin">A Couriers recompence.</note> that I haue gotten there a graye heade, féete full of goute: mouth without
<pb facs="tcp:3663:71"/> téeth: raynes full of grauel: my goodes layde to pledge: my body charged with thought: and my ſoule litle cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed from ſinne. And yet is there more ſeyng that I muſt néedes ſpeake, that is, that I haue returned my body ſo wery, my iudgement ſo dull, my tyme ſo loſt, the beſt of my age ſo paſſed, &amp; that is worſt of all, I found no taſt in any thing that is in the world: ſo that to conclude, I am of my ſelfe all werye of my ſelfe. What ſhould I more tell or ſay of the alteracion of my lyfe, and of the chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of fortune? I came to the court in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, and come from it malicious: I went thither true and meaning truth,<note place="margin">The alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by the court.</note> and returned a lyar: I went thither humble, and returned preſumptuous: I went thither ſober, &amp; returned a gur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and glutton: I went thither gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and humayne, and returned cleane contrary. Finally in goyng thither I marde my ſelf in al points: And I haue no cauſe to laye the faulte in my mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, for the vices bée ſoone learned without a maiſter, &amp; cannot be forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:3663:71"/> without a corrector. O miſerable that I am, I kept in the court an accompt of my goodes, to knowe howe they were waſted, &amp; not for to diſtribute them to the poore: I tooke héede of my honor for to encreaſe it, not for to better my ſelfe by the tyme: I tooke care of them that ſhould paye mee, to knowe what was owyng mée, and not that I might gette to profite the poore withall, but to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite in riches and not in vertue. I held an accoumpt with my ſeruauntes, to none other purpoſe, then to know how long they had béen with me and ſerued mée, and not to enquire what lyfe they led: Finally, I held a coumpt of my life, but it was more to conſerue it, then to correct it.</p>
               <p>Lo, beholde, this was my accoumpt, this was my calculacion, this was the Arſmetrique y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I learned in the court.</p>
               <p>Let vs yet go a litle further and ſée myne exerciſes. I neuer was yet in the court but I founde to whom I bare malice, or els that enuied mée. I was neuer yet in the palaice but I founde a
<pb facs="tcp:3663:72"/> window open, and a courtier murmur. I neuer yet ſpake to princes,<note place="margin">The miſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers of their ſtate.</note> but I we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t from them not contented in my mind with ſome parte of their anſwere. I neuer yet went to bed without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playnt, nor neuer did ryſe without a ſigh. If I went about to doe anye good thing, my great affaires hindered mee. If I wold ſtudy, my felowes letted me. If I went to take any honeſt and quiet paſtyme, mine affayres would not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit mée. If I kept my ſelfe ſolitary and from company, my thoughtes marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red mée:<note place="margin">The lacke of mony a great miſery.</note> Finally there was neuer any thing that ſo vexed my heart as the lack of money in my purſe. And yet all this is nothing, remembring that I was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer enuious to ſuche as were myne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualles: a flatterer to my ſuperiors, and without pitie to mine inferiors: &amp; wher I phanſied one, I bare hate almoſt to all other. I found euery man worthy of reproofe, but againſt my ſelfe I could not ſuffer a worde to be ſpoken. O how forgetfull haue I béen, which ſhoulde forget or a morſell of meate had béen
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:3663:72"/> put in my mouth, &amp; haue talked aloude to my ſelf alone, as it had béen one that had béen mad? O how often hath chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced me that in comming from the coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſail wery, or from the palaice thought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, I would not heare mine owne ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes ſpeake, nor diſpatch ſuch as I had to doe withall? O how many times haue I béen ſo drowned in buſines, that I could not moderate my penſiuenes, although my frendes did counſail mee to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary? O alas, how many times hath my mynde preſſed me to leaue the court and the worlde, and to yelde my ſelfe to ſome ſolitary deſert, as an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remite? becauſe I ſaw the king auau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce him and him, and I put backe as a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon halfe deſperate.</p>
               <p>Moreouer to fulfill my trauailes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies I went aſking &amp; ſerching newes of the affayres of the court: alwayes harkening what one ſaid of another: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſpying and watching: and all this conſidered, I founde by myne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, that I liued in heauynes, capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie, and ſtate of damnacion.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3663:73"/>
               <p>Let vs yet go farther: If I were rich, one or other ſerched ſome meane to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour mée: If I were poore, I found none to ſuccour mée: my frendes cryed out vpon mée, and myne enemyes ſought my death. Ouermuche bablyng of the courtiers brake my braynes: and much ſilence made me to ſlepe, and the ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude cauſed me to be be ſad: And ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much company oppreſſed me: much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe weryed me, and idlenes confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me.</p>
               <p>To conclude, I ſo burdened and vexed my ſelf in the court with ſo much tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uail in naughtines, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I durſt not deſire death, although I had no deſire to liue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>The xix. Chapiter. ¶ The aucthor maketh accoumpt of the vertues that he loſt in the court, and of the eull cuſtomes that he lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned there.</head>
               <p>BVt now to procéede, my fortune paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, my frends died, my force decaied,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:3663:73"/> and my firſt faſhions failed: O if al my paynes had bene ended at the firſte tyme when I came to the court, howe happy had that been for me? but now al conſumed, I complaine ſingulerly of my traitorous hearte, which would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ceaſe to deſire vaine thinges, and the curſed tong to ſpeake ſclaunderous things. O gentle reader, be not weary, if I tell thee in fewe wordes the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt him that I was when I went firſt to the courte, and that I am nowe ſince I haue been in the courte. Firſt and before that I did caſt my ſelf into this perillous labyrinth (which is to ſay a priſon ful of ſnares) I was a good deuout perſon, gentle and feareful and ſince I haue learned to be a miſchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous felowe, ſlowe in doing good, and litle or nothing regarding the welth of my ſoule. I went thether being very yong and of good diſpoſicion, and came from thence deffe, and more then ſpur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blind, and no more able to goe then hee that is ful of the goute: And briefely an olde griſarde, full of ambition, in ſuche
<pb facs="tcp:3663:74"/> wiſe that I am ſo variable, that ſkante I know on what ground to ſet my fete. My hart was of ſo depraued a ſort, that it deſired to be diſcharged of all accio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and yet for all that founde no nother but perill and torment.</p>
               <p>Sondry tymes I purpoſed to leue the court, and ſodenly I repented. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time I purpoſed not to come out of my lodging, &amp; ſtrait wayes I was enforced to trot a trot to the court. Sometime I purpoſed not to come to the palayce, and or I were ware I was compelled to go thither ſometime or it were day. I purpoſed to be no more vexed, and ſodenly my paſſions augmented, And it followed that my good purpoſes ceaſed and went from me: and I did that was leude and naughty. Behold how I ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of wynd and of fooles imaginaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as many a fooliſh courtier doth, I haue phantaſied with my ſelfe (in the court ſometime) that I gouerned the King and the Princes, and that I came of a noble houſe and aunciente ſtock, excelent in ſcience, great in fauor
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:3663:74"/> and beloued of al men, ſage in counſail, moderate in ſpeaking, eloquent in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, prudent in ſeruice, and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to all. But when I waked out of my folly as from a dreame, and looked to my féete, I knew eaſly that I had borne falſe witneſſe to my ſelfe of this golden and pleaſaunt immaginacion, and ſaw of truth in other, the whiche I dreamingly imagyned of my ſelfe.</p>
               <p>I ſerched the waye how to be eſtée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of euery man, holy, wyſe, gentle, content, and of a good zeale, and a ſea of ſadnes. Lo this fault happyned to courtiers as it did vnto me, that is, to ioyne foliſh liberty with vertuous ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure,<note place="margin">Diſordred wil is an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to vertue and honor.</note> which be two thinges that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not agrée, becauſe that diſordinate wyl is enemy to vertu &amp; honor. But for my part good reder, I geue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks vnto god my affections be ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>what waſted &amp; mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tified, for I was wont being in ſeruice to deſire dayly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> court might remoue And now I care not though ſeldome or neuer I come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my houſe. I had a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cial luſt to harken for newes. And now
<pb facs="tcp:3663:75"/> I care not for them at all. I ſawe the time whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I loued not to be out of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, And now I deſire nothing more then to be ſolitary, I was wonte to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyte to heare, to ſée iuglers, daunſers, lyars and dalyars: And now ſo to do, wer to me more then death. In like maner I was wont to ſolace my ſelf in Fiſhing, Hunting, ſhooting in the hack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>but: And now I mind no nother but to bewayle and lament the tyme I haue loſte: and cal to mind the firſt time that the Emperour tooke me into his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, from thence where I was nori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from my tender yeares in greate fere, and not knowing what the world was, but occupied only in my deuocio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and learnings: I often roſe at midnight I comforted the ſick, I red the Goſpell and other good bookes of good doctrin. Breifly, euery man did helpe me to bée good, and chaſtiſed me from euell: If I did well, I was prayſed: if I did euell I was corrected: if I were heuye, I was comforted: if I were angry, I-was appeſed: if in any agony, my fren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:3663:75" rendition="simple:additions"/> prayed to God for me: O what cauſe haue I to repent out of meſure, thus to haue forſaken reſt and Godly lyuyng and to haue enioyed epiſcopall dignity, in which the Emperor ſet me: foraſmuch as a vertuous life is the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of all good, and the Epiſcopall dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity the ſea of all dangier. Loe howe I haue paſſed my good yeres without em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ploying my tyme well, and withoute knowledge what my fortune ſhould be I do therefore admoniſh the reader, to do better then I haue done in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> court, if thou be there, or elſe to forſake it in a better houre then I haue done: for ſo doing thou ſhalt declare thy ſelfe, that thou haſt determined to liue ſagelye &amp; well aduiſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>The .xx. Chapiter. The Auctour taketh his leaue of the world with great eloquence.</head>
               <p>FArewell world, foraſmuche as one can nor may truſt of thee nor in thée
<pb facs="tcp:3663:76" rendition="simple:additions"/> For in thy houſe O world the paſſage is paſt,<note place="margin">The world is not to be truſted.</note> and that which is preſente go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſoone away, and that which is to begin, commeth wonderous late, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as he that thinketh himſelf moſt firm, ſoneſt doth fall, the moſt ſtrongeſt ſooneſt doeth breake, and perpetuities ſooneſt decay, in ſuche ſorte that thoſe which be deſtinate to liue an hundred yeres, thou ſuffereſt him not of all that time, to liue one yere in quiet.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The world is vnthankfull.</note>Farewel world, for as much as thou takeſt and rendereſt not agayne, thou werieſt but comforteſt not, thou rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſt, but makeſt no reſtitucion, thou quarelleſt but doeſt not pacifie, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeſt before thou haue cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playn, &amp; geueſt ſentence before thou he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt the parties, euen till thou kill vs, &amp; then burieſt vs before we dy. Farwell world foraſmuch as in thée,<note place="margin">The pleaſures of the world are mixt with paines</note> nor by thée ther is no ioy without trouble, no pece without diſcord, loue without ſuſpitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, reſt without feare, abundaunce with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fault, honor without ſpot, ryches without hurte of conſcience, nor highe
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:3663:76"/> eſtate but he hath ſomewhat that hée complaineth of.</p>
               <p>Farewel world foraſmuch as in thy palayce promyſes are made and neuer kepte, men ſerue and haue no reward,<note place="margin">the world pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth and performeth not.</note> they are inuited to be deceyued, they la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour to be troubled, &amp; trauaile to take payn, they laugh and are beaten, thou faineſt to ſtaye vs, to make vs fal, thou lendeſt, to pull away ſtraight agayne, thou honoreſt vs to defame vs, and cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>recteſt without mercy.</p>
               <p>Farewell world thou ſclaundereſte them that are in credite,<note place="margin">The world doth vniuſtly.</note> and doeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce the infamed, thou letteſte the traytors paſſe frée, and putteſt true me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to their raunſoms, thou perſecuteſt the peceable and fauoreſt the ſedicious, thou robbeſt the pore and geueſt to the rich, deliuereſt the malicious, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneſt innocentes, geueſt licence to depart to the wiſe, and retaineſt fooles:<note place="margin">The peruerſe and blind iudgement of the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ld.</note> and to be ſhort, the moſt part do what they liſt, but not what they ſhold. Fare wel world foraſmuch as in thy palaice no man is caled by his right name, for
<pb facs="tcp:3663:77" rendition="simple:additions"/> why? they call the raſhe valiaunt: the proude, cold harted, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> importune, dilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, the ſad, peaceable: the prodigall, magnificall: the couetous a good huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band: the babler, eloquent: the ignorant a litle ſpeaker: the wanton, amorous: the quiet man, a foole: the forbearer, a courtier: the tyraunt, noble. And thus thou world, calleſt the counterfeat, the true ſubſtaunce, and the truth the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeat.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The world de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiueth.</note>Farewell worlde for thou deceiueſt all that be in thée: promiſing to the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bicious, honors: to the greedy, to come forward: to the brokers, offices: to the couetous, riches: to the gluttons, ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kettes: to the enemies vengeaunce: to the theues, ſecretnes: to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vicious, reſt: to the yong, time: and to all thing that is falſe, aſſurance.</p>
               <p>Farewell worlde, for in thy houſe fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity is neuer kept, nor truth maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: and alſo we may ſee in thy houſe, one glad and another afrayd: ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercharged: ſome out of the right way: ſome voyde of comfort: deſperate, ſad,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:3663:77"/> heauy ouerburdened and charged, and more then loſt and ſometime both.</p>
               <p>Farewell world foraſmuch as in thy company, he that wenes himſelf moſte aſſured, is moſt vncertaine, and hée that followes thée goeth out of the way and he that ſerues thée, is euell payed: and he that loues thée, is euel entreted, and he that contents thée, contenteth an euell maiſter: and he that haunteth thée is abuſed.</p>
               <p>Farewell world foraſmuch as thou haſt ſuch miſhap, that ſeruices done &amp; preſents offered to thée, profit nothing, nor the lies that is told thée, nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kettes made to thée: nor the faithfulnes we geue to thée: nor the loue we beare to thée. Farewell world, foraſmuch as thou deceiueſt all, backbyteſt all, and ſlaundereſt al, chaſtiſeſt al, threteſt vs al, achiueſt al, &amp; in the end forgetteſt al.</p>
               <p>Farewell world, ſithens in thy company all men complayn, al cry out, al wepe, and all men dye liuing.</p>
               <p>Farewell world, ſithens by thée wée hate eache one the other to the death:
<pb facs="tcp:3663:78" rendition="simple:additions"/> To ſpeke till we lye: to loue, till wee diſpayre: to eate till we ſpue: to drinke till we be dronken: to vſe brokage to robbery: and to ſin, till we dye.</p>
               <p>Farewell worlde for being in thée, we forget our infancy, and our greene age, without experience: our youth in vices, our middle age in turmoyling and buſines: our olde age in lamentaci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons: and all our time counted together in vayn hopes.</p>
               <p>Farewell world, for in thy ſcoole we are led till the heire be white: the eyes blered: the eares defe: the noſtrels drop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyng: the forehed wrinckled: the feete goutie: the raynes ful of grauel: the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack full of euell humors: the head ful of migram: the body full of ſorowe, &amp; the minde full of paſſions.</p>
               <p>Farewel world for none of thy louers come to good profit, witnes thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly we ſée, are not falſe knaues marked in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> face, theues hanged? ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quellers headed? robbers by the hye wayes ſette vpon wheles? heretikes brent? falſe mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney makers boyled, killers of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:3663:78"/> torn in pieces, and other diuers puniſhmentes of ſuch as are great in fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uour with thee? Farewell world foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as thy ſeruauntes haue no more paſtyme, but to trot by the ſtreates, to mock one another? to ſeke out we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches? to ſende preſentes: to beguile yonge girles: write amorous letters, ſpeke to bandes: play at the dice: plede agaynſte their neighbour: tel newes: inuent lies, and ſtudy new vyces. Farewel world for in thy pallayce none wil doe good to other for the bore fightes agaynſte the Lyon: the Vnycorne agaynſt the Coco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dryl: the Eagle agaynſt the Vultur: the Elephant agaynſt the Mynotaure: the Sacre, agaynſt ehe Kyte: the maſtyf, agaynſt the Bull: One man agaynſte another: and al together againſt death.</p>
               <p>Farewell worlde,<note place="margin">All fighte againſt deth.</note> becauſe thou haſte nothing, but to our ruin: For of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the yearh openeth afore our feete: the water drounes vs: the fire burnes vs: the ayre miſtempers vs: the Wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doth kil vs: the Sommer doth chafe vs, the dogges doth byte vs, the Cattes
<pb facs="tcp:3663:79"/> doth ſcrat vs: the Serpents doth poyſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, the flyes doth prick vs: the Flees doeth eate vs: and aboue all, worldlye buſines deuoures vs:</p>
               <p>Farwel world ſeing no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can pas thi domynyon in ſuertie, for in euery path we finde ſtones to ſtumble at? bridges that breakes vnder vs? Snow that let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs: Mountaynes that wery vs: Thunders that feares vs: Theues that robbe vs, encounters that hurts vs, and euil fortune that killes vs.</p>
               <p>Farewell worlde, foraſmuch as in thy country there is litle health: for ſome be lippers &amp; ſome haue the french pockes: ſome the Canker, and ſome the goute: and ſome haue the foule euell, &amp; ſome the <hi>Sciatica,</hi> and ſome the ſtone, and ſome <hi>Quotidian</hi> feuers: ſome wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dring feuers: ſome <hi>tercian</hi> and <hi>quarten</hi> feuers: ſpaſmes, palſies, and the moſte parte ſicke of fayre folly.</p>
               <p>Farewell world, foraſmuch as there is not a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in thy houſe but hee is noted with ſome defaute in his perſon: For if there be any talle manne, the reſte
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:3663:79"/> is lubberlyke. If he haue a faire face, his eye ſhall be too blacke: If he haue a good forehead, it ſhalbe wrinckeled: If he haue a welfauored mouth, he ſhal lacke téeth: If he haue fayre handes, he ſhall lacke faire heire, And if hee haue fayre heire, hee ſhall haue a foule ſkinne.</p>
               <p>Farewell worlde, foraſmuch as the inhabitauntes in thee are ſo variable of maners and condicions, that ſome will folow the court, ſome wil ſayle on the ſea: &amp; if one would be a marchaunt, the other will be a huſbandman: If the one will be a hunter, the other will be a fiſher: If one wil gouerne a Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, the other vnder pretence of that, will pyll and poll the poore people.</p>
               <p>Farewell worlde, foraſmuch as in thy houſe there are none that prepare themſelues to liue, &amp; much leſſe to dye: And yet we ſee ſome dye young, &amp; ſome in middle age, ſome in olde age, ſome dye by hanging, &amp; ſome by drowning: ſome dye for hunger, &amp; ſome in eating, ſleping, and reſting, and ſome or they
<pb facs="tcp:3663:80"/> beware, and for the moſt parte or they looke for death.</p>
               <p>Farewell worlde, foraſmuch as we can neither knowe thy diſpoſicion nor condicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: For if one be wiſe, another is a foole: If one be fyne, another is of a groſſe witte: If one be valiant, another is a coward: If one be geuen to peace, another is ſedicious: And if one be of a ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle ſpirit, another is very froward.</p>
               <p>Farewell world, ſeyng no man can liue with thée: for if a man eate to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, he becommes weake: if to muche, he waxeth ſicke: if a man labour, ſtrait he is wery: if he be idle, he liueth beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: if he geue litle, he is called a nigard: if he geue much, he is called prodigall: if a man viſite his frendes often, he is called importune: if to ſeldome, full of diſdayne: If a man ſuffer wrong, he is called falſe hearted: And if he doo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, then is he wilfull: If hee haue frendes, he is prayſed: If enemyes, he is purſued: If one tary to lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in a place, he waxeth wery: and if he chaunge to ofte, he is grudged at. Finally, I
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:3663:80"/> ſay, that ſuch thinges as diſpleaſe me, I am forced to folowe, and that which I would, I cannot come by.</p>
               <p>O world vncleane, I coniure thée thou filthy world, I pray O thou world, and proteſt againſt thee thou worlde, that thou neuer haue parte in mee, for I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund nor deſire nothing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is in thée, neyther hope of any thing in thee, for I haue determined with my ſelf that <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſui finem curis, ſpes, et fortuna va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lete.</hi> I haue finiſhed world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cares, therfore hope and fortune fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3663:81" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>nor</p>
                  <p>w</p>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of William Norton</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>¶Printed by VVilliam NORTON.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3663:81"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
